Why do they call you the dando investor?
他们为什么叫你“笨蛋投资者”？
&gt;&gt; It's a way of doing business and making
这是一种
money without taking risk. Like for
无需承担风险即可开展业务和赚钱的方式。
example, Mr. Gates, Mr. Walton, Mr.
例如，盖茨先生、沃尔顿先生、
Branson, all of these people followed
布兰森先生，所有这些人都遵循
these simple mental models. So if they
这些简单的思维模式。 所以如果他们
won, they would win big and if they
赢了，他们会赢得很多；如果他们
lost, they'd lose nothing.
输了，他们也不会损失什么。
&gt;&gt; So I want to know everything.
所以我想知道所有的事情。
&gt;&gt; Okay, let's start with this. Monish
好的，我们就从这里开始。 莫尼什·
Pabry is the self-made millionaire who
帕布里是一位白手起家的百万富翁，他
built one of the most respected
创建了
investment firms in the world, managing
世界上最受尊敬的投资公司之一，管理着
over a billion dollars. And now he's
超过十亿美元的资产。 现在他为
giving us the simple tools and
我们提供了
frameworks to create life-changing
创造改变人生的
wealth.
财富的简单工具和框架。
&gt;&gt; If humans understood that if I embark on
如果人们明白，如果我以
a business in a format where the risk is
风险接近于零的方式开展一项业务
close to zero, more people would do it.
，就会有更多的人效仿。
And that's what these mental model do.
这就是这些心智模型的作用。
For example, cloning. We are taught if
例如，克隆。 我们从小就被教导，如果
you want to start a business, you need
你想创业，就需要
to come up with something new. But
想出一些新的东西。 但
actually, if you are a great cloner, you
实际上，如果你是一位优秀的克隆人，你
will be 90% ahead of the rest of
将比其他人领先90%
humanity. And in fact, everything that
。 事实上，
Microsoft has done well at has come from
微软取得的所有成功都源于对
copying someone on the outside. And then
外部企业的模仿。 然后
there's time. When you're starting a
还有时间。 当你
business, don't quit the day job because
创业时，不要因为
some other yo-yo is paying your rent.
有人帮你付房租就辞掉现在的工作。
But it does mean that you need to find
但这意味着你需要抽出
time to work on your business. But I
时间来经营你的事业。 但我
will show you the perfect way to
会向你展示
allocate your time. And that's not all.
分配时间的最佳方法。 但这还不是全部。
There's models like lowhanging fruit,
还有一些模型，例如“唾手可得的成果”、“利益
skin in the game, givers versus takers,
攸关”、“付出者与索取者”
and the circle of competence. And I'll
以及“能力圈”。 我会一一
I'll explain all of them. What about
解释清楚。 那么
investing? Cuz you're very well known
投资呢？ 因为你是一位非常有名的
for being an excellent investor.
优秀投资者。
investing. And there's also something
投资有三件重要的事情。 还有一种
known as the rule of 72, but I wish they
叫做“72法则”的东西，但我希望
would teach it more in high school. And
高中能多教教它。
it tells us how long it takes money to
它告诉我们资金翻倍需要多长时间
double. Now, this is exciting.
。 这真是令人兴奋。
&gt;&gt; I see messages all the time in the
我经常在
comment section that some of you didn't
评论区看到有人留言说他们没有
realize you didn't subscribe. So, if you
意识到自己没有订阅。 所以，如果您
could do me a favor and double check if
能帮我个忙，再次确认一下
you're a subscriber to this channel,
您是否是本频道的订阅者，我
that would be tremendously appreciated.
将万分感激。
It's the simple, it's the free thing
这是件简单又免费的事情，
that anybody that watches this show
任何经常观看本节目的人都
frequently can do to help us here to
可以做，以帮助我们
keep everything going in this show in
保持本节目目前的良好发展
the trajectory it's on. So, please do
势头。 所以，请您
double check if you've subscribed and uh
再次确认是否已订阅，
thank you so much because in a strange
非常感谢，因为从某种意义上说
way, you are you're part of our history
，您是我们历史的一部分，
and you're on this journey with us and I
您与我们一起踏上了这段旅程，我
appreciate you for that. So yeah, thank
为此感谢您。 所以，谢谢
you
你，
Monish Pabry. With the work that you do
莫尼什·帕布里。 结合你所做的工作
and the sort of public educating that
以及
you've done more recently in your
你近期在
career,
职业生涯中从事的公共教育工作，
what is the message you're trying to
你想要传达的信息是什么
convey? If you had to summarize that
？ 如果让你用一句话概括这条
message and exactly who are you trying
信息，以及你究竟想把
to convey it to?
它传达给谁？
&gt;&gt; It really depends on uh what message.
这主要取决于信息的内容。   在
last few decades. When you have uh kind
过去的几十年里，我总结出了几种不同的思维模型。 当你
of clarity on these mental models and
对这些思维模型有了比较清晰的认识，
especially when you can start overlaying
尤其是当你能够开始将它们叠加起来的时候
them, that's when you get 1 + 1 becomes
，你就会明白 1 + 1 等于
11. And uh so these mental models are
11。而且，这些思维模型
not all in the same direction or in the
并不是都朝着同一个方向发展，也不是都属于同一个
same genre.
类型。
&gt;&gt; So just to pause there for a second. So
所以我们先暂停一下。 所以，就是“
the the word mental models
心智模型”这个词
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。   这
&gt;&gt; means it's basically a framework for
意味着它本质上是一个
thinking.
思考框架。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes.
。
&gt;&gt; So one framework for thinking is this
因此，克隆的概念就是一种思考框架
idea of cloning.
。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes.
。   举个
&gt;&gt; Um as one such example.
例子。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes. Let's take the mental model of
。 让我们以克隆的思维模型为例
cloning.
。
&gt;&gt; Cloning.
克隆。
&gt;&gt; Cloning. Right. So um
克隆。 正确的。 所以
what we are taught is that if you want
我们学到的是，如果你
to start a business, you need to come up
想创业，你需要
with something new, something that
想出一些新的东西，一些
hasn't been done before. But the reality
以前从未有人做过的事情。 但现实
is that the world will very easily
是，世界很容易接受
accept three of the same thing or five
三个相同的事物，或者五个
of the same thing. And usually it is an
相同的事物。 通常来说，
advantage to look at something that
观察
already exists and say can another one
已经存在的事物并思考是否可以再
of those exist for example or can I take
创造一个类似的事物，或者能否对
what's there and tweak it a little bit.
现有事物进行一些调整，都是很有优势的。
So there's something peculiar in the
所以，
human psyche maybe going back into our
人类的心理中可能存在某种奇特的现象，可以追溯到我们的
history and our ancestral evolution
历史和祖先进化时期，在这种现象中，
where humans look down upon cloning. But
人类瞧不起克隆。 但举例来说，
the greatest cloners I think in human
我认为人类历史上最伟大的两位克隆人
history were Bill Gates and Sam Walton.
是比尔·盖茨和山姆·沃尔顿。
Now, we think of Bill Gates as an
现在，我们认为比尔·盖茨是一位
innovator and we think Sam Balton
创新者，我们认为萨姆·巴尔顿
created Walmart, which was also new. But
创建了沃尔玛，沃尔玛也是一家新公司。 但
actually, they're both meto models.
实际上，它们都是镜像模型。   如果
Microsoft would not have existed without
没有强大的克隆能力，微软就不会存在
being a great cloner. So, when we look
。 所以，当我们
at um Microsoft Word, it came from Word
回顾微软 Word 时，它其实源自 WordPerfect，而 WordPerfect
&gt;&gt; which was a company
是微软
&gt;&gt; which a competitor that he took out. Uh
收购的竞争对手公司。
we look at Excel, it came from Lotus. Uh
我们来看看Excel，它源自Lotus。
we look at Bing, it came from Google.
我们来看看必应，它来自谷歌。
And you know what Bing is, but it's not
你知道必应是什么，但它不是
Google. Everything that Microsoft has
谷歌。 微软取得的所有成功都
done well at has come from copying
源于对
someone on the outside. And when we look
外部企业的模仿。 当我们看看
at Sam Walton, who's you know, the
山姆·沃尔顿，也就是
Walton family, if you pull them all
沃尔顿家族，如果把他们所有人
together, it's the richest family in the
加起来，那就是世界上最富有的家族
world. It's richer than uh Elon and
。 它比埃隆和
everyone. And Sam Walton, by his own
所有人都富有。 山姆·沃尔顿自己也
admission, would tell you that he has no
承认，他没有任何
original ideas. So, originally Walmart
原创的想法。 所以，沃尔玛最初是
cloned Sears and Kmart.
模仿西尔斯和凯马特的。
&gt;&gt; For my international listeners, these
对于我的国际听众来说，这
are two big supermarket chains.
是两家大型连锁超市。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And they're both gone. They they
。 他们俩都走了。 他们，他们。
And in fact, Walmart buried them. And um
事实上，沃尔玛把他们埋葬了。 嗯，
and Sam Walton
山姆·沃尔顿
was one of the most intense cloners
是有史以来最狂热的克隆人之一
ever. So if he was driving on vacation
。 所以，如果他开车
with his family and he's passing some
带着家人度假，路过一家
retail store, he would tell his family
零售店，他就会让家人
to stay in the car and he would go in
待在车里，自己进去
the store just to check it out. And he
逛逛。 他
said that there is there is no human who
说，
has lived in history or will live in the
历史上没有一个人，将来也不会有人
stores than he has.
比他逛过的零售店更多。
One time there was a manager of his and
有一次，他有个经理，
he would go in with his managers to
他会带着经理们一起去
these stores. Retail is one of the most
这些商店。 零售业是
transparent businesses. You can go into
透明度最高的行业之一。 你走进
your competitor's store and you'll
竞争对手的店铺，10分钟就能
figure out the entire business model in
弄明白他们的整个商业模式
10 minutes. You don't need to talk to
。 你不需要和
them. Okay? It's beautiful. So, he went
他们说话。 好的？ 很美丽。 于是，他
into this retail store and the manager
走进了这家零售店，经理
says to him, "Oh, what a terrible
对他说：“哦，这
operation. The whole store was topsy
生意糟透了。整个店都乱
tur."
成一团。”
And Sam says to him, "Yeah, but did you
山姆对他说：“是啊，但是你
see the candle display? The candle
看到蜡烛展览了吗？蜡烛
display was fantastic." So, Sam felt
展览太棒了。” 所以，山姆觉得
that he could learn from anyone. It
他可以向任何人学习。
didn't matter if you were a useless
无论你是水平很差的
operator, a great operator or whatever,
操作员、水平很高的操作员，还是介于两者之间的任何水平，都无关紧要
anyone in the middle. Walmart is just an
。 沃尔玛只不过是
amalgamation
融合了
of ideas from other places. If we look
其他地方的一些理念。 如果我们
at if you look at a company like
看看像星巴克这样的公司
Starbucks,
，
we think of Starbucks as innovative, but
我们会认为星巴克是创新的，但
actually what Howard Schultz did is he
实际上霍华德·舒尔茨所做的，是他
saw a concept in Italy and his idea was
在意大利看到了一个概念，他的想法是，
that I think this is work in the US,
我认为这在美国是行得通的，
right? And so he cloned he cloned that
对吧？ 于是，他把
idea from Italy and brought that coffee
意大利的这个想法复制到了美国，并将那种咖啡
shop experience to the US. If you are a
馆体验带到了美国。 如果你是一位
great cloner,
优秀的克隆人，
you will be 90% ahead or 95% of the rest
你将领先90%或95%的
of humanity. Now
人类。
another mental model humans have this
另一种人类的思维模式是，他们认为
that starting a business
创业
is risky. In reality entrepreneurs do
是有风险的。 实际上，企业家
not take risk. They do everything in
并不承担风险。 他们竭尽所能将
their power to minimize risk. And in
风险降到最低。 在
many cases when they embark on a
许多情况下，当他们开始
business the risk approaches zero. What
创业时，风险接近于零。 朝
is extremely risky is a 9 to-ive job
九晚五的工作风险极大，
because we have one life,
因为我们只有一次生命，
right? And it goes away and you may not
对吧？ 然后它就消失了，你可能就无法去做
get to do what's in your heart. You may
你内心真正想做的事了。
not get your music out, right? And so
你的音乐可能无法发行，对吧？ 所以，
getting our music out is really
把我们的音乐推广出去真的非常
important. So, so this notion which is
重要。 所以，这种从小就被
drilled into us that if you're an
灌输给我们的观念——如果你是
entrepreneur, you're taking risk really
企业家，你就是在承担风险——实际上
kind of does a big disservice to most
对大多数人来说是一种很大的误导
humans. And if if humans understood that
。 如果人类明白，
if I embark on a business, I can do it
如果我开始创业，我可以采用
in a format where the risk is zero or
风险为零或
close to zero and I can clone an
接近于零的方式，而且我可以复制一个
existing business.
现有的企业。
Right now you've combined two mental
现在你已经结合了两种思维
models
模型，
and we can start adding more to them.
我们可以开始向其中添加更多内容了。
But two has become 11. 1 plus 1 has
但是 2 变成了 11。1 加 1
already become 11. It's nonlinear. And
已经变成了 11。它是非线性的。 那
why is it that why is why am I saying
我为什么会说
that entrepreneurs do not take risk? So
创业者不愿承担风险呢？
if I take my own case as an example and
以我自己的情况为例，
I can give you a hundred cases like that
我可以举出一百个类似的例子，
but if I take my own case as an example
但我以我自己的情况为例，
I was working 9 to5 at a company and I
我当时在一家公司朝九晚五地工作，我
had a business idea my employer expected
有一个创业想法，我的雇主希望
me to work 40 hours a week right there's
我每周工作 40 小时，
168 hours in the week so I felt like
一周有 168 小时，所以我觉得
there must be at least another 30 40
至少还有 30 到 40
hours there that could work
小时可以用来做
on my startup.
我的创业项目。
&gt;&gt; Could you show me this in context of
你能把它放在正确的语境中给我解释一下吗
&gt;&gt; right? So if we look at our whole week
？ 例如，如果我们回顾一下我们整个星期的情况，看看
for example these beautifully arranged
这些排列精美的
Legos if I take one of these blocks of
乐高积木，如果我拿起其中一块
Legos. So each one of those blocks in
乐高积木。 所以，里面的每个模块都是
there is 2 hours. So 8 hours a day. We
2 小时。 所以每天8小时。 我们
sleeping 8 hours a day right?
每天睡8小时，对吧？
&gt;&gt; And uh and we're doing that 7 days a
而且我们一周七天都在这样做
week. Right? So basically we've got 7
。 正确的？ 所以基本上我们
days a week, 8 hours a day we're
一周7天，每天8小时都在
sleeping. The blue Legos are showing our
睡觉。 蓝色的乐高积木代表我们
40 hours a week. Uh 8 hours a day, 5
每周工作 40 小时。 呃，我们每天工作 8 小时，
days a week we're working. Right? Then
每周工作 5 天。 正确的？ 然后
we get to
我们就开始做
other, you know, uh preparing dinner and
其他事，你知道，比如准备晚餐、
showering, shaving, getting ready,
洗澡、刮胡子、做准备
whatever else. So that's about 4 hours a
等等。 所以，工作日每天大约需要 4 小时
day on the weekdays, which is uh
，
including commute time, and about 8
包括通勤时间；
hours a day on the weekend. Then we get
周末每天大约需要 8 小时。 然后就到了
to free time, you know, social media and
空闲时间，你知道，刷刷社交媒体，
watching Netflix and hanging out with
看看 Netflix，和
friends, going for dinner. And we've got
朋友们出去玩，吃顿饭。 我们有很多
quite a bit. We've got about 4 hours a
。 我们每天大约有 4 个小时的时间
day of doing that and about 8 hours a
做这件事，周末每天大约有 8 个小时的时间做这件事
day on the weekends. So this is kind of
。 所以，这大概就是
typical what a typical week for most
大多数人典型的一周生活
people would look like. Right
。
&gt;&gt; now, when you're starting a business,
现在，当你创业的时候，最
the important thing is don't shut off
重要的是不要切断
the cash flow. Some other yo-yo is
现金流。 有人在
paying your rent and some other yo-yo is
帮你付房租，有人在
paying your groceries. So, we don't want
帮你买菜。 所以，我们不想
to rock the boat, but we're going to
节外生枝，但我们打算
make one change to blue,
对蓝色做一处改动，
&gt;&gt; which is the amount of hours I'm working
那就是我朝九晚五的工作时长
for my 9 to5.
。   在
&gt;&gt; Now, before I started my startup, um I
我创办自己的公司之前，嗯，我
used to get top reviews as an employee.
曾经是一名评价很高的员工。
uh you know I was very focused on doing
你知道，我一直专注于
a great job for my employer allin right
为我的雇主做好工作。就在
the day I decided I'm going to run do my
我决定创办自己的公司那天，
startup I decided I need to be just
我决定我的
above firing level my performance needs
业绩只需要略高于被解雇的水平，只要
to be just good enough so they don't can
足够好，不至于被解雇就行，不能再多了，
me but nothing beyond that because I
因为我
need all my energy to go into my startup
需要把所有的精力都投入到我的创业公司中。
so that's the only tweak I'm making is
所以，我唯一做的调整就是
the blue stays but we're not doing extra
保留蓝色元素，但我们不会像
blues like we were doing before. Right.
以前那样额外使用蓝色元素了。 正确的。
&gt;&gt; And blue for anybody that doesn't can't
而对于那些因为听音频而看不见的人来说，蓝色就是一种
work.
工作。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. Yeah. Blue is work. Exactly.
确切地。 是的。 蓝色代表工作。 确切地。
Now, when we embark on a startup,
如今，当我们创办一家公司时，
we should never do a startup to make
我们绝不应该以
money. It's the worst reason to start a
赚钱为目的。 这是创办公司最糟糕的理由
company. The purpose of business is not
。 商业的目的并非仅仅是为了
to make money.
赚钱。
The purpose of business is to deliver an
企业的宗旨是
incredible product or service to
为人类提供卓越的产品或服务
humanity.
。
If you do that, the money is a side
如果你这样做，金钱只是附带的
effect. It'll happen. We don't need to
结果。 这会发生。 我们不需要
focus on it. So, what we are looking for
关注这件事。 所以，我们正在寻找的
is do we have a product or a service
是，我们是否有正在考虑的产品或服务
that we are thinking about that we could
可以
bring into this world that is going to
带到这个世界上，并以
improve the world in some way? How do I
某种方式改善世界？ 我怎么
know if it's a good idea?
知道这是否是个好主意？
&gt;&gt; Whatever idea you have come up with is
你想出的办法
not going to work.
行不通。
Okay?
好的？
Because you came up with it in an ivory
因为这是你闭门造车、闭门造车想出来的
tower between your ears. Okay? And
。 好的？ 而
that's not really a great place to find
那里并不是寻找
great ideas.
好点子的好地方。
What's going to happen is we're going to
接下来我们将
be doing what I call rapid prototyping
进行我称之为快速原型制作的过程，也就是
which is we take this idea and show
我们将这个想法展示给
humans what it is and when you show it
人们看，当展示
to humans you will get feedback. So I'll
给人们看时，你会得到反馈。 所以，我……我还是用
more practical terms.
更实际的方式来解释吧。
uh when I was um uh when I was starting
呃，当我……呃，当我开始
my first business uh it was going to be
创业的时候，呃，它是
a IT services business okay information
一家IT服务公司，好吧，信息
technology services and I was going to
技术服务公司，我打算为那些
earnings or cash flows. Um, I was in a
收入或现金流达数十亿美元或以上的大型企业公司提供这些服务。 嗯，当时我正在
meeting with a a senior IT guy at a very
和芝加哥一家大型银行的一位高级IT人员开会，
and I was going through my PowerPoint
我正在向他展示我的PowerPoint演示
deck with them.
文稿。
I came to the 10th slide,
我讲到第 10 张幻灯片，
said my spiel, went to slide 11. So the
说完我的演讲稿，然后转到第 11 张幻灯片。这时，
boss who was sitting in the meeting
坐在会议室里的老板
said, "Go back to slide 10."
说：“回到第 10 张幻灯片。”
So I went back to slide 10 again gave my
于是我又回到第 10 张幻灯片，继续讲
speech that I had for slide 10 and took
我为第 10 张幻灯片准备的演讲稿，然后讲到第
it to 11. He said go back to slide 10
11 张幻灯片。他说回到第 10 张幻灯片，
and do not change the slide.
不要更改幻灯片。
I don't have an interest in any other
我对其他幻灯片都不感兴趣
slide. Okay. So I took it back to slide
。 好的。 所以我把话题拉回到第
10 and all he wanted to talk about was
10 张幻灯片，而他只想谈论第
what was on slide 10. My deck was
10 张幻灯片上的内容。我的幻灯片
talking about
讲的是
seven things we could do. Slide 10 was
我们可以做的七件事。 第 10 张幻灯片是这
one of those seven.
七张幻灯片之一。
It was an extreme pain point for him. He
这对他来说是一个极大的痛点。 他
needed help on that one thing. He didn't
在那件事上需要帮助。 他
need help on all the other riff raff
不需要我帮忙处理
stuff I was talking about. So when
我刚才说的那些乱七八糟的事情。 所以，在
you're doing a startup,
创业的时候，
you have to be listening very carefully.
你必须非常认真地倾听。
Your customers or potential customers
您的客户或潜在客户
will tell you exactly what you need to
会准确地告诉您需要
do. Whatever you came up with may be 80%
做什么。 你想出的办法可能只有 80% 的
right or 70% right or 40% right, but
正确率，也可能只有 70% 的正确率，或者只有 40% 的正确率，但
your customer will tell you what is 100%
你的客户会告诉你什么是 100%
right.
正确的。
&gt;&gt; Okay? Because that's a real pain point.
好的？ 因为那确实是个痛点。
So I went back and thought about it and
所以我回去仔细想了想，
I realized that his pain point and I
我意识到他的痛点——而且我
could see it was a severe pain point
能看出这是一个严重的痛点，
because he gave me a purchase order at
因为他在会议结束时给了我一份采购订单——将会
be a pain point for a lot of people. So
是很多人的痛点。 所以
I went back I took slide 10 blew it up
我回去把第 10 张幻灯片扩展
into 20 slides and that became the deck.
成 20 张幻灯片，就成了现在的演示文稿。
Okay. Everything else got thrown out
好的。 其他东西现在都被扔掉了
right now. I couldn't have done that
。 没有他，我不可能做到
without him.
。
My brain is too small to have figured
我的脑子太小，想不明白
that out. So, anytime you're doing a
。 所以，无论何时你进行
startup of any kind and you have a
任何类型的创业，并且你有一个
prototype or a early product or
原型、早期产品或
something going on,
其他正在进行的项目，
your users are going to tell you exactly
你的用户都会告诉你
what tweak they want.
他们想要做出哪些调整。
&gt;&gt; You've just reminded me of a
你让我想起了
conversation I had this morning.
今天早上的一次谈话。
&gt;&gt; Okay. Yeah, where I interviewed someone
好的。 是的，我今天早上面试了一个人，
because much of what you're saying is
因为你说的很多内容都
orientated towards startups, but it's
与创业公司有关，但
actually every single day of everyone's
实际上它与每个人的
life because I interviewed someone this
日常生活息息相关，因为我今天早上面试了一个人，他应聘的是
the company. And this person has spent
公司里一个非常重要的职位。 这个人曾
20 years at one of the biggest companies
在世界最大的公司之一工作了20年
in the world. And when I was doing the
。 在
interview, she was telling me about lots
采访过程中，她跟我讲述了
of things she's done in those 20 years.
她这 20 年来所做的许多事情。
And I was just trying to get to this one
我当时只是想达成这个目标
thing. Can you put on events? And she
。 你们能举办活动吗？ 她
was telling me about this and that and
跟我讲了这个、那个、还有这个、这个、
the other thing and this and this and
还有
the other thing. And I was just actually
那个。 其实
I'd only come to this interview to
我来参加这次面试只是为了
figure out if she could do put on big
弄清楚她是否有能力举办大型
scale events. So we spent of an hour
活动。 于是我们聊了一个小时
conversation. We spent 55 minutes
。 我们花了55分钟
talking about a bunch of things I wasn't
聊了一堆我根本不
interested in. And actually as you were
感兴趣的事情。其实在你
speaking I was going you know what she
说话的时候，我一直在想，你知道她本来
could have done at the start of that
可以在谈话一开始就那样做的吗？
conversation. She could have gone
她本来可以走的。
Stephen can I ask you one question? What
斯蒂芬，我可以问你一个问题吗？
is the what are you looking for from
你希望从这
this person?
个人身上得到什么？   如果那样的话，
&gt;&gt; And if and then I would have gone I just
我就去了，我只
want someone that can put an event and
想要一个能组织活动的人，
then the next 55 minutes could have been
然后接下来的 55 分钟可能都在
persuading me that she can do that.
说服我她能做到这一点。
&gt;&gt; Sure. And it just applies to what you
当然。 这正好适用于你
just said there. How could you of the as
刚才说的话。 以你现在所掌握的知识，作为
the saleserson that day in that meeting
那天会议上的销售人员，如果
have done a better job without going
没有
through all of those slides?
看过那些幻灯片，你怎样才能做得更好？
&gt;&gt; Well, I think what what I would do now
嗯，我想
if I were doing something like that is
如果我现在要做类似的事情，我会把
that my my radar
我的
on listening would be 10x.
监听灵敏度提高 10 倍。
You know, we don't learn when we speak.
你知道，我们说话的时候是学不到东西的。
M
我们通过倾听来学习。 所以我会
really be trying to talk less and
尽量少说话，
extract more.
多获取信息。
&gt;&gt; And um I wouldn't even rely so much on
而且，我甚至不会太依赖
slides. I'd like to really try to bring
幻灯片。 我真的很想让
them in into what they are trying to
他们理解他们想要表达的意思
say. and uh and and so basically in uh
。 所以，基本上，
if if you study if you study businesses
如果你研究商业，比如风险投资、
you know ventureback non-benture back
非债券投资等等，你会发现，
whatever this is a very common thing
这其实很常见：
there are almost no businesses
几乎没有企业
who end up with the business model that
最终能完全按照
was originally conceived I mean that
最初设想的商业模式发展下去。我的意思是，这种情况
just is would be such an anomaly it's
简直太罕见了。真正
which really leads to taking this wet
促成企业成功的，是创始团队和早期客户之间的互动，他们就像把一块湿
clay and making into something that
黏土捏成
people want,
人们想要的东西。
&gt;&gt; you know, and so you know, if you think
所以，想想谷
of something like uh Google Glass, you
歌眼镜，
know, when they came up with those
当他们推出这款
glasses that they thought the whole
眼镜的时候，他们认为
world was going to wear.
全世界都会戴上它。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; So, it didn't work. Well, why didn't it
所以，这个方法行不通。 那么，为什么它没有
work? Well, the reason it didn't work is
奏效呢？ 之所以行不通，是因为
you're talking about something extremely
你谈论的是极其
personal. Okay? Like for example,
私人的事情。 好的？ 例如，
Wrigley's chewing gum. Okay. My mouth is
箭牌口香糖。 好的。 我的嘴巴是
a very personal space. I'm not going to
非常私密的部位。 我不会
put Gloss Chewing gum in there.
把 Gloss 口香糖放进去。
&gt;&gt; What's chewing gum?
口香糖是什么？
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; Okay. Yeah.
好的。 是的。
&gt;&gt; You're not going to put some brand
你不会去买
that's half the price of Wrigley's.
价格只有箭牌一半的牌子吧。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; In there. Because you don't want to go
里面。 因为你不想去
there. That's not of interest to you. So
那里。 你对此不感兴趣。 所以，
when we wear glasses or sunglasses or
我们戴眼镜、太阳镜或其
anything we wear, that's very personal.
他任何饰品，都是非常私人的事情。
So the the ergonomics and the human
所以，如果设计上稍有偏差，人体工程学和人为
factors are very important if it's
因素就显得非常重要了
slightly off. Now Meta is trying to do
。 现在 Meta 也想做
the same thing. But they went to RayBan,
同样的事情。 但他们去了雷朋眼镜店，
right? They did a JV with Rayban.
对吧？ 他们与雷朋公司成立了合资企业。
Those glasses look like normal glasses.
那副眼镜看起来像普通的眼镜。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; I think there's a higher chance.
我认为可能性更大。
&gt;&gt; Well, I've got some. We used them. Yeah.
嗯，我有一些。 我们使用过它们。 是的。
&gt;&gt; You don't have any Google Glass?
你没有谷歌眼镜吗？
&gt;&gt; No, no, no, no, no. I mean, I think they
不，不，不，不，不。 我的意思是，我觉得他们
they cut the project, didn't they?
砍掉了这个项目，对吧？
Google. So, so what I'm trying to say is
谷歌。 所以，我想说的是，
that we we have to pay very close
我们必须非常
attention to the customer. Uh I mean
关注客户。 呃，我的意思是，
Steve Jobs was right. The customer
史蒂夫·乔布斯是对的。 顾客
doesn't know what he wants. Okay. But if
不知道自己想要什么。 好的。 但如果
you put it in front of them, then they
你把方案摆在他们面前，他们就
can now tweak and tell you exactly what
可以进行调整，并告诉你
they want.
他们到底想要什么。
&gt;&gt; Right. So, so that and that's another
正确的。 所以，这就是另一种
mental model which is now we get to the
思维模式，现在我们来看
third model which is that you're not
第三种模式，那就是
smart enough if whatever founding team
如果你的创始团队不够聪明，无法
out what people want. Period. So you
弄清楚人们想要什么，那么你就不够聪明。 时期。 所以你
have to have very good listening skills
必须具备非常好的聆听技巧，
and you have to be have the flexibility
并且要有灵活性，
to and again when you're listening
在聆听时将
separate the signal from the noise right
信号与噪声分开，正确地
take in what is real signal and ex leave
提取出真正的信号，例如忽略
out what is the noise and then you're
噪声，然后你就会
starting to get down a path which is
开始走上一条
going to make more sense.
更有意义的道路。
&gt;&gt; The other thing that's kind of a model
另一个
maybe woven into there was this idea of
融入其中的理念是
just like attention to detail. I'm not
注重细节。 我甚至
even sure if that's a model, but when
不确定那是不是一个模型，但当
you told me about the Walmart founders
你告诉我沃尔玛的创始人
laying between the aisles to measure the
躺在货架之间测量
exact centimeter of length, the model
精确到厘米的长度时，
there for me was just like precision and
对我来说，那个模型就代表着精准和
detail.
细节。
&gt;&gt; It's a game of inches. I mean, what I'm
这是一场毫厘之争。 我的意思
saying is that uh when when Sam Walton
是，当山姆·沃尔顿
was trying to figure out the name of the
在为
company, one of the reasons he went with
公司起名时，他选择沃尔玛的原因之一
Walmart was it was seven letters and he
是它只有七个字母，他当时正在考虑在
in his stores and he was trying to come
商店里安装招牌的成本，他想找
up with a name with the fewest letters
一个字母最少的名字，
because it costs less.
因为这样成本更低。
&gt;&gt; Okay. And so I mean cost
好的。 所以我的意思是，沃尔玛的
cost sensitivity is all over the place
成本敏感度参差不齐
in Walmart, right? I mean that's just
，对吧？ 我的意思是，这不正是
front and center with what they do,
他们工作的核心
right? They just really squeeze blood
吗？ 他们简直能把石头里的血都榨
out of a rock, you know? So basically, I
出来，你知道吗？ 所以基本上，我的
mean, I think that was and that's the
意思是，我认为那就是
reason why they became so successful.
他们取得如此成功的原因。
in business is your cost. you you may
在商业活动中，成本始终是你能够掌控的因素之一。 你可能
not be able to control your margins and
无法控制利润率、
selling prices and a lot of other things
售价以及许多其他因素，
but you can always control cost so
但你总能控制成本。所以
that's another model where you have to
这是另一种需要自律的模式，
&gt;&gt; you have to have very strong discipline
你必须在成本方面有非常严格的自律。
on the cost side if you look at
看看像
something like LVMH you know uh the guy
LVMH这样的公司，你知道，
who runs it I mean he's in luxury goods
经营它的那个人，我的意思是，他经营的是奢侈品，是
he's in high-end
高端品牌，
&gt;&gt; LVMH make Louis Vuitton and
LVMH旗下有路易威登，是的，
&gt;&gt; yeah yeah I mean everything you know is
我的意思是，
you know they've ten over Tiffany's
你知道，他们的价格比蒂芙尼高出十倍，所有品牌都是如此
everyone. Um, but when you look at how
。 嗯，但是当你了解
the company is run, it's very tight.
这家公司的运作方式时，你会发现它的管理非常严格。
He spends money on the best real estate
他把钱花在最好的房产上，
because that's important. But the deals
因为这很重要。 但你知道吗，
he negotiates on those real estate is
他在那些房地产交易中达成的协议简直令人
mind-blowing, you know. So, it's it's a
难以置信。 所以，这是一项针对
very tightlyun operation on a product
一个未必需要如此严格监管的产品类别的严格监管行动
it. M
。
&gt;&gt; but that's why they that's why he's
但正因如此，他才
become the wealthiest guy in Europe
成为了欧洲首富，
&gt;&gt; because that mentality will then apply
因为这种心态会应用
to every decision.
到他做出的每一个决定中。
&gt;&gt; Absolutely.
绝对地。
&gt;&gt; And if you apply it to 100 things, it
如果将此应用于 100 件事，它确实会产生
does matter.
影响。
&gt;&gt; Oh, it does matter big time. Yes.
哦，这非常重要。 是的。
&gt;&gt; So I have these yellow blocks here which
这里有一些黄色方块，
represent working hours working on your
代表你经营自己业务的工作时间
own business. Yes.
。 是的。
&gt;&gt; So show me how you would take some of
那么请告诉我，你会如何移除其中的一些
these blocks away.
障碍。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes.
。
&gt;&gt; And introduce hours working on your own
并安排时间从事自己的
business.
事业。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So basically it's it's really
。 所以其实
quite simple. Well, we're not really not
很简单。 嗯，我们其实不会去
going to mess with our sleep cycles.
打乱我们的睡眠周期。
We're going to leave that alone.
我们决定不再赘述。
&gt;&gt; Sleep staying the same.
睡眠状况保持不变。
&gt;&gt; And uh we we need our blue, which is our
我们需要我们的蓝色，也就是我们的
work work space 40 hours. We need that
工作空间，每天工作 40 小时。 我们需要这种情况
to continue. One of the changes we're
继续下去。 我们将要做出的改变之一
going to make is we're going to live
是，我们将住在离
close to work. So, we're going to cut
工作地点近的地方。 所以，我们要
down commute time as much as we can.
尽可能缩短通勤时间。
&gt;&gt; Okay?
好的？
&gt;&gt; Because every hour matters, okay? So,
因为每一小时都很重要，好吗？ 所以，
the area that we're going to focus on is
我们将重点关注的领域是
the free time. Okay? And the reason why
空闲时间。 好的？ 之所以
taking out the free time is not a
抽出空闲时间不是
problem is because what we are embarking
问题，是因为
on like we just discussed is not about
我们刚才讨论的这件事并不是为了
making money. Is getting our music out.
赚钱。 把我们的音乐传播出去。
&gt;&gt; Getting our music out. What do you mean
把我们的音乐传播出去。 你这话是什么意思
by that?
？
&gt;&gt; Which means that we have something in us
这意味着我们身上拥有一些
that we know the world needs and we want
我们知道世界需要的东西，我们想把
to bring it to that world. We want to
它带给这个世界。 我们想把
bring it to the world and because we
它带给全世界，正因为我们
want to bring it to the world, it's not
想把它带给全世界，所以这就不算
work. I think the audience might be
工作了。 我认为观众可能会
challenging themselves in their head and
在心里质疑自己，
saying, "But I love my the thing I do
心想：“但我热爱我的
for work. I'm I'm one of maybe the rarer
工作。我可能是少数
puppies every day and I love that."
每天都能和幼犬一起工作的人之一，我非常喜欢这份工作。”   是的
Yeah. So, I think that I think this is
。 所以，我认为这
not for everyone. So, I think you have
并不适合所有人。 所以，我认为你必须
to ask yourself who you are. If you are
问问自己，你是谁。 如果你
truly excited about your 9-to-five job
真的对朝九晚五的工作
and what you're spending your main
以及你大部分
working main waking hours on, awesome.
清醒时间所做的事情感到兴奋，那就太棒了。
That's great. I mean, everyone's not
那太棒了。 我的意思是，不是每个人都会
going to be an entrepreneur. Everyone's
成为企业家。 并非每个人都能创办自己的公司
not going to have a startup. Everyone
。 每个人都
they they may be getting their music out
可能
in a different way on someone else's
通过其他平台以不同的方式发布自己的音乐
platform, which is perfectly fine. And
，这完全没问题。 但是，但是，如果
but but if if that is not you, where
那不是你，如果
when you go to work, you're not super
你去上班时，
excited to get up in the in the morning
早上起床并不感到特别兴奋，
and you're not tap dancing to work every
每天上班也不会兴高采烈、手舞足蹈
day. If that's not happening, then
。 如果这种情况没有发生，那就说明有
there's something wrong. And you have to
问题了。 你必须
ask yourself well is there something
问问自己，是否还有
else that is that you're passionate
其他你充满热情
about that you want to do and this is
想要做的事情，而且这件事
not something that should take a lot of
不应该花费太多
effort. So if you go back and look at
精力。 所以，如果你回顾一下
for example Bill Gates and Paul Allen,
比尔·盖茨和保罗·艾伦的例子，
right? I mean, Bill Gates is at Harvard
对吧？ 我的意思是，比尔·盖茨当时在哈佛大学，
and he sees a magazine which shows a
他看到一本杂志，上面展示了一台
very early personal computer and he
非常早期的个人电脑，他
realizes that there's a paradigm shift
意识到这是一个范式转变，
and he realizes that he needs to be part
他意识到自己需要参与其中。
of it and Paul Allen is the one who sent
保罗·艾伦把
him that magazine and he told Bill, "We
那本杂志寄给了他，并告诉比尔：“我们
got to go do this now. This is our time
现在就得行动起来。现在是我们的时代了
now." And for Bill, it was a very easy
。” 对比尔来说，这是一个非常容易的
decision.
决定。
Very easy decision. Very difficult for
很容易做出决定。 对
his parents. His parents were in shock
他的父母来说非常艰难。 他的父母对
that he's going to abandon his uh
他要放弃
degree. And you know, he he told his
学位感到非常震惊。 你知道，他告诉
parents, "Don't worry about it. I'm
父母：“别担心，我会
going to come back and I'll finish the
回来完成
degree." And several decades later,
学业的。” 几十年后，
Harvard gave him an honorary day. and
哈佛大学授予他荣誉日称号。
his parents were in the audience and he
他的父母当时也在观众席上，他
told them, "I told you I'd come back,
告诉他们：“我告诉过你们我会回来，
finish it off." Right?
完成这件事。” 正确的？
&gt;&gt; I put some numbers to this. 12% of
我对此进行了一些量化分析。
people according to the stats that are
根据目前收听节目的听众的统计数据，有 12% 的人
unsatisfied with their job, which means
对自己的工作非常不满意，这意味着
they hate it. 85% of workers globally
他们讨厌自己的工作。 全球 85% 的员工
are disengaged, meaning they're not
缺乏工作热情，这意味着他们
fully invested or happy at work. So,
对工作没有全身心投入，也不快乐。 所以，
it's a huge number of people. More than
人数非常庞大。 超过
half of the US workers are at least
一半的美国员工至少在
somewhat satisfied, but engagement
某种程度上感到满意，但员工敬业度
remains worryingly low. So if we look at
仍然低得令人担忧。 所以，如果我们看一下
that 85% number, 85% of workers globally
85% 这个数字，那就是全球 85% 的员工对
work. So it's really those
工作缺乏热情，也就是说，他们对工作没有全身心投入，也没有感到快乐。 所以，真正重要的是那些
&gt;&gt; sure
确定的
&gt;&gt; people and and the thing is it's not
人，而且问题是，
it's not just enough to be unhappy at
仅仅在
work. That's one piece of it. the the
工作中感到不快乐是不够的。 这是其中的一部分。 这种
unhappiness can be a symptom and uh one
不快乐可能是一种症状，而其
of the one of the causes can be that you
原因之一可能是你的
have a different calling in life and you
人生使命不同，而你却
are not following following your
没有追随你的
calling. Now
使命。
sometimes for someone like Bill Gates
有时候，像比尔·盖茨
for example and Paul Allen they figured
和保罗·艾伦这样的人，他们找到了
out their calling and they just went
自己的使命，然后就一路向前；但对
right for many of us it may not be that
我们很多人来说，这可能并不
easy. So what we have to do is we have
容易。 所以，我们需要做的就是
um try a few things. You know you try on
尝试一些事情。 你知道，试穿
different shoes to see what fits. And so
不同的鞋子才能找到合适的。 所以，
you know have some thought experiments.
你可以做一些思想实验。
Talk to your friends. You know say okay
和朋友们聊聊。 你知道，比如说，好吧，
you know I'm a UPS driver. this is what
你知道我是个UPS司机。 这就是
I do and I really like playing the
我做的事，我真的很喜欢弹
guitar or I like to make these art
吉他，或者在家制作这些艺术小
figurines or something at home and
雕像之类的东西，
whatever else, right? So, you have to
等等等等，对吧？ 所以，你必须
figure out what your calling is and I'm
弄清楚你的使命是什么，而我
probably not the best person to tell you
可能不是告诉你
how to figure out what the calling is.
如何找到使命的最佳人选。
Maybe another guest of yours can can uh
或许你的其他客人可以
can help them with that.
帮他们解决这个问题。
&gt;&gt; Do you think everyone has a calling?
你认为每个人都有自己的使命吗？
Yeah, I mean I think I think we are all
是的，我的意思是，我认为我们都是
unique children of God and I think we
上帝独一无二的孩子，我认为我们
uh we all have some music we want to get
每个人都有一些想要
out and uh knowing what that is and
表达的音乐，而知道那是什么并把它表达出来
getting it out may not be the easiest
可能不是件容易的
thing but it's a worthwhile journey to
事，但这是一段值得
try to get there. Right? So, we can't do
尝试的旅程。 正确的？ 所以，我们不能
this just because we're dissatisfied and
仅仅因为不满现状就去做这件事，也
we can't do this just because we want to
不能仅仅因为想要
make money and get rich. We've got to
赚钱致富就去做这件事。 我们必须做出
have something that we think the world
一些我们认为全世界
would be interested in. And
都会感兴趣的东西。
you know, in my case, I I'd gone through
你知道，就我而言，我曾和
session with a couple of industrial
几位工业
psychologists and they told me, "Monish,
心理学家进行过一次咨询，他们告诉我：“莫尼什，
you like to play games. You're a game
你喜欢玩游戏。你是个游戏
player." And actually, they couldn't be
玩家。” 事实上，他们的说法再
more accurate. So when I was doing my
准确不过了。 所以，当我创办
startup,
公司的时候，
um I'm I'm a numbers guy and a math guy.
嗯，我是一个喜欢数字和数学的人。
So I actually like that. So what I used
我其实挺喜欢这个的。
to do is because I had no money, I used
因为我没钱，所以我以前
to send 200 letters a week to these
每周都会给
senior IT people at 200 different
200 家不同公司的高级 IT 人员寄 200 封信
companies. But what I did is so all
。 但我所做的，是让所有
these people I was sending this letter
这些我寄信的人
to, they had a gatekeeper, some
，都安排了守门人、
secretary etc. whose job was to not let
秘书等等，他们的工作就是不让
anything through. And my whole purpose
任何信息通过。 我这么做的目的就是为了让
was I need this letter to get through.
这封信能寄出去。
It needs to get through the gatekeeper.
它需要通过守门人的关卡。
So I was using mailmerge which was mass-
所以我使用了邮件合并功能，批量
prodducing these letters. But there was
生成了这些信件。 但是
a customization the mail word where if
邮件内容有一个自定义设置，例如，如果
person some person's name was David
收件人是 David
Smith. It said dear Dave. Okay. And then
Smith，则邮件内容会显示为 David Smith。 它说，亲爱的戴夫。 好的。 然后，
throughout the letter it talked Dave.
整封信里都在谈论戴夫。
Dave's name came up like three four
戴夫的名字出现了三
times. When assistant got the letter she
四次。 助理收到信后，
couldn't tell whether I know Dave or not
无法判断我是否认识戴夫，
&gt;&gt; because you used his shortened name.
因为你用了他的简称。
&gt;&gt; His shortened name. And she doesn't want
他的简称。 她不想把
to throw a letter that somebody that he
信扔给认识他的人
knows. So the letter would go through
。 这样信件就能被
&gt;&gt; enough times. Right now what I also did
多次传递。 现在，我做的另一件事
is one week after those letters were
是，在这些信件送达一周后，
I called I made 200 calls. I called all
我打了 200 个电话。 我给所有
200 people and basically if I got
200 个人都打了电话，基本上如果听到
voicemail, left a message, whatever else
语音留言，就留言，或者其他任何方式，
right now they have entered the
现在他们都进入了
salesunnel. Okay. So Dave Smith is in
销售流程。 好的。 所以戴夫·史密斯现在身处
the salesunnel. If I get no response
销售隧道。 如果一周后我仍然没有收到
from Dave Smith, after one week there's
戴夫·史密斯的回复，我会再打
one more call. Then the calls start
一次电话。 然后通话
getting spaced out double time. 2 weeks
间隔开始以两倍的速度延长。 提前 2 周
out, then four weeks out, then 8 weeks
，然后提前 4 周，然后提前 8 周
out, then 16 weeks out. But Dave never
，然后提前 16 周。 但戴夫始终没有
leaves that funnel. Okay? Until he tells
离开那个漏斗。 好的？ 直到他告诉
me, "Do not bother me anymore and I have
我“别再打扰我了，我
no interest," they're going to stay in
没兴趣了”，他们才会停止
that funnel. So the second week I send
被打扰。 所以第二周我
out another 200 letters, make another
再寄出 200 封信，再打
200 calls, right? And now I've got the
200 个电话，对吧？ 现在我有了
first week, second week. So you can see
第一周和第二周的安排。 所以你可以看到，
as time goes on, I'm calling non-stop,
随着时间的推移，我一直在不停地打电话，
&gt;&gt; right? Because this thing is
对吧？ 因为这件事是……
&gt;&gt; But what I was tracking, because I'm a
但我一直在追踪的是，因为我是个
math guy, what I was tracking is, okay,
数学家，我一直在追踪的是，好吧，
these 200 letters went out. How many
这 200 封信已经发出去了。
people did I get any kind of positive
我收到了多少人的积极
response from? Right? because not
反馈？ 正确的？ 因为并不是
everyone's telling me to get lost. Okay.
每个人都叫我滚开。 好的。
And how many meetings am I having? And
我一共要开多少次会议？
what is the ratio of calls to meetings,
通话次数与会议次数、会议次数与成交次数的比例是多少？
meetings to close, etc. And
等等。
my ticket size of the item I was selling
我销售的产品的单价
was very large, hundreds of thousands of
非常高，达数十万
dollars. Right?
美元。 正确的？
9 months after doing this where now
9 个月后，我们
let's go back here. So we're going to
回到这里。 所以我们要
take our free time. So what I'm trying
利用空闲时间。 所以我想
to describe is that what I'm doing is
表达的是，我正在做的事情
actually more exciting than the orange.
实际上比做橙子更令人兴奋。
The yellow is more exciting than the
黄色比橙色更令人兴奋
orange. So basically
。 那么，
&gt;&gt; what is the yellow?
黄色到底是什么呢？
&gt;&gt; The yellow is our startup.
黄色代表我们的创业公司。   这
&gt;&gt; So that's working on your startup.
就是你创业的过程。
&gt;&gt; So on on the weekends I'm going to do 10
所以周末我打算
hours a day because I'm not working,
每天工作 10 个小时，因为我不用上班，
right? And on the weekdays, I'm going to
对吧？ 工作日我
do four hours a day because I've got
每天只做四个小时，因为我还有
other things to do because I have a job
其他事情要做，比如工作
and whatever else is going on. So
和其他事情。 所以，
there's my weekdays,
我的工作日是每周
5 days there where I'm putting in 4
5 天，每天工作 4
hours a day and then I'm putting in 10
小时，周末则工作 10
hours on the weekend. And the free time,
小时。 而空闲时间，远不如
this is not as exciting as pounding
痛扁
Dave.
戴夫来得刺激。
Pounding Dave continuously till he says
不断地鞭打戴夫，直到他说“
either get off my back or here's your
别烦我了”或者“这是你的
purchase order is very exciting. It's
订单”，这真是太刺激了。 这比
way more exciting than playing some
玩
social media or watching Netflix or
社交媒体、看Netflix或
whatever else
其他
&gt;&gt; which is what people currently do with
人们目前用来消磨
their free time.
空闲时间的事情要有趣得多。
&gt;&gt; So one of your one of the litmus tests
所以，判断
you need to you should be doing a
你是否需要
startup or not is yellow
创业的试金石之一就是：黄色
needs to be more exciting than orange.
必须比橙色更令人兴奋。
Your startup needs to be more exciting
你的创业项目必须
than your free time.
比你的空闲时间更精彩。
for you and going on Facebook or
对你来说，Netflix 应该非常无聊，上 Facebook 或
Instagram whatever should be very boring
Instagram 之类的东西也应该非常无聊，
&gt;&gt; compared to building your company.
相比之下，创建自己的公司就令人兴奋了。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes.
。
&gt;&gt; So you know um the Pink Floyd song, we
所以你知道，嗯，Pink Floyd 的那首歌，《我们
don't need no education.
不需要教育》。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; We don't need no thought control.
我们不需要思想控制。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. We don't need none of this. This
。 我们根本不需要这些。 这
is so useless. You understand how
完全没用。 你明白
useless this is? Yellow is where it's
这样做有多么没用吗？ 黄色才是王道
at. It's not It's not the orange stuff.
。 不是，不是那种橙色的东西。
We don't need this. Thank you, Stephen.
我们不需要这个。 谢谢你，斯蒂芬。
&gt;&gt; So, we don't need any free time.
所以，我们不需要任何空闲时间。
&gt;&gt; This is better than free time.
这比空闲时间好多了。
&gt;&gt; Building your business.
打造你的事业。
&gt;&gt; You're having an orgasm every hour.
你每小时都会达到性高潮。
&gt;&gt; So, what can you what what can be better
那么，你觉得还有什么
than this? Much of what I do here when
比这更好的呢？ 我在这里进行
I'm having these conversations is I'm
这些对话时，大部分时间都在
trying to put myself in the shoes of the
尝试设身处地地站在那些朝
nineto-five job and they've got an idea
九晚五上班的人的角度思考，他们有一个想法，
and their idea is isn't really hasn't
但这个想法还没有真正实现，
the the pressure they're feeling in
他们现在感受到的压力
their lives is is probably now a
可能来自
financial one like they want financial
经济方面，比如他们想要经济
freedom. They want more optionality in
自由。 他们希望生活中有更多选择，
their lives to be able to go on holiday,
能够去度假，
make more choices and have more freedom.
做出更多选择，拥有更多自由。
If you're that person, um what are the
如果你就是这样的人，那么，为了从零到一，你需要考虑哪些
mental models that we haven't discussed
我们还没有讨论过的思维模型呢
to get from zero to one?
？
&gt;&gt; So, one of the things to keep in mind is
所以，需要记住的一点是，
that we live in a world now where most
我们现在生活在一个创业过程中，大多数
things that you would want to do in
你想做的事情
terms of starting a business are not
都不需要
capital intensive.
大量资金的世界里。
&gt;&gt; What does that mean?
这意味着什么？
&gt;&gt; Doesn't take much money. In fact, what's
不需要花很多钱。 事实上，
been happening over time is startups
随着时间的推移，创业公司
need less and less and less money
需要的资金越来越少，
because they need more and more and more
因为它们需要的脑力越来越多
brain power, right? So, the good news is
，对吧？ 所以，好消息是，
a gating factor is not that you need
阻碍因素并不是你需要
money. When when I started my business,
钱。 我刚开始创业的时候，为了赚钱，
I took on I signed up for every credit
我申请了所有
card that would come to me. So, I had
能申请到的信用卡。 所以，我大概有十几张 Visa 和 Mastercard 信用卡，总共有
70,000 in unused credit lines in
7 万美元的未使用信用额度，
right? I had about $30,000 in my
对吧？ 我的退休账户（401k）里大约有 3 万美元，
retirement account, my 401k, which I
我
also took out. I said 25, I can make
也把这笔钱取出来了。 我说的是25，我可以
that up later, right? So, basically, I
之后补上，对吧？ 所以，基本上，我
had $100,000 of capital and uh that
有 10 万美元的启动资金，而这
100,000 got used because once I got
10 万美元很快就用掉了，因为一旦我开始
going, I needed working capital and so
运营，我就需要流动资金
on. And but then the business was the
等等。 但后来发现，这家
business was actually cash flow
企业的现金流实际上是
positive. 9 months after I was doing
正的。  9 个月后
this,
，
I was able to get rid of this.
我终于摆脱了这个问题。
So after 9 months, my business was
所以9个月后，我的公司
producing
产生了
enough cash flow that I went and
足够的现金流，于是我
resigned. Okay. And uh yeah, we can we
辞职了。 好的。 嗯，是的，我们也
can put that in here as well. So what
可以把它放在这里。 于是，
happened is that I went to my boss and
我去找了我的老板和
his boss and basically told them that
他的老板，告诉他们
I'm
我
started a business. it's not competitive
创业了。 它与公司没有竞争力，
leaving in 2 weeks and this is my two
两周后就要离开了，这是我的
weeks notice and basically that was that
两周通知期，基本上就是这样。
right and you know they they sat me down
你知道，他们让我坐下来，
and said you know monish we were so
说：“莫尼什，过去
confused for the last 9 months because
9个月我们一直很困惑，因为
we met several times because we saw big
我们见过你好几次，我们看到
drop off in your performance but it was
你的业绩大幅下滑，但从来没有
never so low that we wanted to fire you.
低到让我们想解雇你。”
I said, "Exactly. That was exactly what
我说：“没错。这正是
I was trying to do. I was trying to say
我想要表达的意思。我的意思是，火力
just above firing level." He said,
刚好高于开火线。” 他说：
"Well, you mastered it because we we met
“嗯，你掌握了这项技能，因为我们见过你好
several times, but we couldn't get rid
几次，但我们就是摆脱不了
of you." So, they what they told me is
你。” 所以，他们告诉我的是：
they said, "Look, when your business
“听着，不是说你的生意会不会
fails,
失败，
not if your business fails. When your
而是当你的生意失败的时候
business fails, please come back. We'll
，请你回来。我们
give you more money. You're going to get
会给你涨工资，你会得到
a promotion, and we'd love to have you
晋升，我们非常欢迎你
back."
回来。”
I could immediately come back. So I said
我可以马上回来。 所以我说
I got one free shot.
我还有一次免费机会。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; Where I leave my job, I go,
我离开工作岗位后，就去那里，
&gt;&gt; I do this thing and if it doesn't work,
做这件事，如果不行，
I'm back to almost exactly where I was.
我几乎又回到了原来的位置。
Almost no change. Right.
几乎没有变化。 正确的。
&gt;&gt; Amazon's type one, type two decision-m.
亚马逊的第一类、第二类决策。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And so, and this is not just me.
。 所以，这不仅仅是我个人的感受。
What risk did Bill Gates take? Okay.
比尔·盖茨承担了什么风险？ 好的。
Bill Gates, what is his value as a
比尔·盖茨作为一名
Harvard freshman in the job market?
哈佛大学新生，在就业市场上的价值如何？
Zero. Okay. He nobody would pay him
零。 好的。 没人愿意付钱给他
anything. And he could come back anytime
。 他随时可以回来
and finished a degree. So let's say he
完成学业。 假设他
went to New Mexico, things didn't work
去了新墨西哥州，结果并不顺利
out. He's got wealthy parents in
。 他在西雅图有富裕的父母
Seattle. Okay? He just comes back,
。 好的？ 他回来后，
graduates a year later, and he goes on.
一年后毕业，然后继续前进。
So what was the risk? There was no risk.
那么风险是什么？ 没有风险。
And if you study entrepreneur after
如果你研究一位又一位企业家
entrepreneur after entrepreneur, what
，
you're going to find, so if we look at
你会发现，比如
Sir Richard Branson,
理查德·布兰森爵士，
he wants to start an airline. Okay? Now,
他想创办一家航空公司。 好的？ 现在，
to start the airline, you need a jumbo
要创办这家航空公司，你需要一架
that costs like 150 million.
价值约 1.5 亿美元的巨型 747 客机。
&gt;&gt; The plane.
飞机。
&gt;&gt; The plane, right? That's some serious
飞机，对吧？ 那可是一大笔钱
money.
。
Richard Branson got Virgin Atlantic off
理查德·布兰森
the ground with zero and with zero risk.
以零成本、零风险的方式创办了维珍航空。
So here's what he did. You replace
所以他是这么做的。 你
capital with creative thinking. So he
用创造性思维代替了资本。 于是他
calls 2065551212
拨打了 2065551212，
which is directory assistance in
这是
Seattle, Washington, and he asked for
华盛顿州西雅图的电话号码查询服务，他询问
the phone number for Boeing. Okay. So he
波音公司的电话号码。 好的。 于是他
calls the main Boeing switchboard.
拨打了波音公司的总机电话。
&gt;&gt; Boeing sell the planes, right?
波音公司出售飞机，对吧？   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Boeing makes the 747. So he calls
。 波音公司生产747客机。于是他打电话给
the main switchboard of Boeing, giant
波音公司（一家规模庞大的公司）的总机，
huge company, and says, "Uh, I'd like to
说：“呃，我想
lease a jumbo." And they hang up on him.
租一架巨型客机。” 然后他们挂断了他的电话。
Okay. He calls about 30 times. And they
好的。 他打了大约 30 次电话。 他们
keep hanging up. And finally, they get
一直挂断电话。 最后，他们
tired of his calls and the lady says,
厌倦了他的电话，那位女士说：
"Let me put you in touch with somebody
“我帮你联系一下
who's in charge of leasing and they can
负责租赁的人，他们会让
tell you to get lost." Okay. So she
你滚蛋。” 好的。 于是她
transfers him to a person who's actually
把他转给了一个实际
leasing jumbos and this person tells
租赁巨型客机的人，这个人告诉
Richard says look Mr. Branson in every
理查德说：“布兰森先生，我们在每个
country we have one customer and in the
国家都只有一个客户，在
UK that is the British that is British
英国，我们的客户就是英国
Airways so we have nothing to talk
航空公司，所以我们没什么好谈的
about. So he says well just humor me for
。” 所以他说，好吧，就让我先满足一下吧
a second. He said, "If British Airways
。 他说：“如果英国航空公司
called you and said that they wanted to
打电话给你，说他们想
lease a old used jumbo, do you have one
租一架旧的二手巨型客机，你手头有没有
lying around?" So the guy says, "As a
闲置的呢？” 所以那个人说：“
matter of fact, we do, but that's
事实上，我们确实有，但这只是
academic." He says, "Well, what would
学术探讨。” 他说：“那么，
you lease it to British Airways for?"
你打算以多少钱租给英国航空公司呢？”
Just since we're having a conversation,
既然说到这儿了，那就顺便提一下，
what ended up happening is Boeing leased
最后波音公司把
him that jumbo. And the reason they
那架巨型客机租给了他。 他们之所以
leased him that jumbo is they had one
租给他那架巨型飞机，是因为他们正好有一架
just sitting around. So they didn't
闲置着。 所以他们
really have any risk because they said
其实没有任何风险，因为他们说
the moment the guy doesn't make any
一旦这个人不
payments, we're going to pull the plane,
付款，我们就会取消飞机，
&gt;&gt; right? So now when you have an airline,
对吧？ 所以现在如果你开航空公司，
you sell all the seats 4 months in
所有座位都要提前4个月售出
advance. The cash has already come in.
。 款项已经到账。
You pay for the fuel 30 days after the
燃油费在飞机落地30天后支付
plane lands and you pay for the lease
，租赁费
after the plane lands. You don't need
在飞机落地后支付。 你不需要
any capital.
任何资金。
Virgin Atlantic got off the ground with
维珍航空白手起家，没有
zero capital. Okay. Now if you can start
一丝一毫的资金。 好的。 如果你能用
an airline with needs a jumbo with zero
零资本创办一家需要巨型客机的航空公司
capital, you can start any business with
，那么你就能用零资本创办任何企业
zero capital. Okay. So, so basically
。 好的。 所以，基本上
when you look at business after business
当你观察一家又一家企业时
after business, all of them what they do
，你会发现它们都是从小
is they start small, they're embionic,
规模起步，逐步发展，
they minimize risk, they get a few
尽可能降低风险，获得一些
customers and then after that they just
客户，然后就
roll with the customers, right? And then
顺应客户的需求，对吧？ 然后
that's how they get going. So,
他们就开始行动了。 所以，
so the important thing is that when we
重要的是，当我们
take the blue out, when blue is no
把蓝色去掉，当蓝色
longer here,
不再存在时（蓝色代表
&gt;&gt; which is work,
工作，
&gt;&gt; which work is gone, yellow is going to
工作消失了），黄色
almost double or triple because this is
几乎会翻倍或三倍，因为这是
where all the orgasmic activity is.
所有性高潮活动发生的地方。
&gt;&gt; So, we move the work, we quit the 9
所以，我们调整了工作安排，辞掉了那份朝九晚五的
toive job and we move that time over to
工作，把那段时间转移到了
work.
工作上。
&gt;&gt; I was I I was working on my startup like
我当时每天
from 7:00 to 9:00 in the morning and
早上7点到9点都在忙我的创业项目，
then I would come back 6:00 p.m. and
然后下午6点才回来。 一直
work till 10 or 12:00 in the evening.
工作到晚上10点或12点。
when you had a job?
你以前有工作的时候？
&gt;&gt; When I had my job and then I'd work on
我以前有份工作，
the weekends and I was so desperate to
周末也会去工作，我当时非常渴望能
just go full-time into it because I just
全职投入其中，因为我当时
said, "If you just let me go full-time,
就想，“如果你们让我全职投入，
I can tear it up." And that's exactly
我一定能做得非常出色。” 事情果然如此
what happened. I mean, we in about five
发展。 我的意思是，我们
first year we did 400,000 revenue,
第一年收入大约是 40 万美元，
second year 1.4 million, third year 3
第二年是 140 万美元，第三年是 300
million, and by the sixth or seventh
万美元，到了第六年或第七
year we were at about 15 17 million. It
年，我们的收入就达到了 1500 万到 1700 万美元左右。 它
just grew because basically then I had
之所以发展壮大，是因为当时我基本上
no shackles on me, you know, I could
没有任何束缚，你知道，我可以
just go full out, right? And the engine
全力以赴，对吧？ 引擎里
I knew all the statistics of these
我知道这些信件的所有统计数据
letters, so many calls, so many this, so
，这么多通话，这么多这个，这么
much this means this and all of that
多这个意味着这个等等，
&gt;&gt; and uh it works. So and and if if it
嗯，它运行正常。 所以，如果这
doesn't work, you can go back to your 9
行不通，你可以回去继续朝九晚
to5 and give it another shot, you know.
五的工作，然后再试一次，你知道的。
So you actually could do this a few
所以你实际上可以重复
times. I think that's a really
几次。 我认为这是一个被严重
unappreciated framework as you call it
低估的框架，
or mental model which is because you
或者说是思维模型，因为你
said you sent 200 letters. I so many
说你寄出了 200 封信。 我
times kids come up to me in the street
经常在街上遇到孩子，
and they say look I've been looking for
他们会说：“你看，我一直在找
a job. I've sent six emails.
工作。” 我已发送了六封电子邮件。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; And they go no one's got back to me.
他们说没人回复我。   是的
&gt;&gt; And you can see that it's hit their
你可以看出这打击了他们的
confidence and now they've actually
自信心，现在他们实际上已经
arrived at the conclusion that getting a
得出结论，找
job is like harder and possible cuz they
工作变得更加困难和不可能，因为他们
sense six.
感觉到了六。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; Now when I interview people like you
现在我采访像你这样的人时，
they all give me much bigger numbers.
他们给出的数字都比这大得多。
they say 200, 300, 5, you know, and
他们说 200、300、5，你知道，
there's something in this sort of law of
这种平均法则里有些东西，就像
more swings, you know, you see it in
多尝试几次一样，你知道，你在
like cricket.
板球比赛中就能看到这一点。
&gt;&gt; My my daughter when she was uh
我女儿
graduating from Berkeley came to me and
从伯克利毕业的时候来找我，
I was really surprised. She said, I want
我真的很惊讶。 她说：“我想
to work at a hedge fund. And so I I said
在对冲基金工作。” 于是我说，
okay. And her degree was not in
好的。 而且她的学位也不是
business. So she was not a natural
商科。 所以她原本根本不在
candidate to be even considered. I said,
考虑之列。 我说，
uh, can you make a list of every hedge
呃，你能列出
fund in New York and LA and put it in
纽约和洛杉矶所有对冲基金的名单，并把
managing partner's name, address? Now,
管理合伙人的姓名、地址放到 Excel 表格里吗？ 现在，
we don't know people's email addresses,
我们不知道人们的电子邮件地址，
but we know everyone's mailing address.
但我们知道每个人的邮寄地址。
Okay. The mailing address is a public
好的。 邮寄地址是公开
piece of data.
信息。
&gt;&gt; The address,
地址，
&gt;&gt; the address is easy. Yeah. Right. And I
地址很简单。 是的。 正确的。 我
I said that uh so she she got a list of
说过，她拿到了一份
funds in LA and New York. And I said,
洛杉矶和纽约约 1200 个基金的名单。 我说：
"What you're going to do is uh you're
“你要做的就是，呃，你
going to ask for the job, but you're
要去应聘这份工作，但同时你要在后面附上
going to have two pages behind that
两页纸，
giving them a stock tip. You're going to
给他们推荐一家股票。你要向
give them a pitch that you have written
他们推介你
up of a company that if they invest in,
写好的一家公司，如果他们投资这家公司，
they're likely to make money." We sent
很可能会赚钱。” 我们寄出了
the 1200 letters, physical letters,
1200封信，是纸质信件，
okay? all physical letters, no email,
好吗？ 全部都是纸质信件，没有电子邮件，
right? And um there's a 85 year old guy
对吗？ 嗯，纽约有一位 85 岁的老人
in New York who gets the letter. He's
收到了这封信。 他已经
retired. The fund doesn't exist. It
退休了。 该基金并不存在。 不管怎样，它本来
shouldn't have been on the list,
就不应该出现在名单上
whatever. But he has a friend in LA. He
。 但他在洛杉矶有个朋友。 他
says, "Hey, Jamie, weren't aren't you
说：“嘿，杰米，你不是在
looking for an analyst?" And this girl,
找分析师吗？” 而这个女孩，
she seems to have the perfect kind of
她似乎拥有完美的成长
background. and she ends up with a
背景。 最终，她的
higher salary than anyone who went to
薪水比任何一个从
Berkeley business school with a much
伯克利商学院毕业、
higher GPA than hers. I was thinking
GPA 比她高得多的人都要高。 我一直在思考
what you're saying um and I made a video
你刚才说的话，嗯，前几天我做了一个视频，
the other day which I think is somewhat
我觉得有点
relevant where I was trying to describe
相关，我在视频里试图
to people how to send a message to
向人们描述如何以一种能
someone in a way that creates impact and
产生影响的方式向他人发送信息，以及
the framework that I came up with which
我想出的框架（我会
I'll I'll we'll animate on the screen
在屏幕上做动画演示），
but is basically so this axis here is
基本上，这个轴代表
you're using. Mhm.
你所使用的渠道的信号与噪声。 嗯。
&gt;&gt; So a high signal channel is one where it
所以，高信号通道是指信号能够
gets past the PA.
通过功率放大器的通道。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; It's less saturated, less busy. A high
这里饱和度较低，人也不多。 与此
noise channel, which is the opposite,
相反，高噪声渠道是指向贵
press at your company.com's email. So
公司邮箱的媒体发送邮件。 所以
like everyone goes through that path and
每个人都会经历这个过程，但最终却
it doesn't get doesn't get to the
无法真正影响到这个
person. And then the other axis is
人。 而另一个维度则
basically the emotional impact of the
主要体现在信息的情感冲击力上
message.
。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; So high emotional impact is doing what
所以，要想产生高情感冲击力，就像
you said, put a stock tip in there,
你说的，在里面放一条股票内幕消息，
you're going to stand out, they're going
你就会脱颖而出，他们会
to think you're a little bit strange. or
觉得你有点奇怪。 或者
what you said about like shortening the
就像你说的，缩短
name that creates more emotional
名称可以产生更多情感
resonance and then low would just be
共鸣，而低端内容只是
&gt;&gt; AI slop copy and paste jargon and really
人工智能生硬复制粘贴的术语，真正
like the most successful messages are up
成功的讯息都在
here.
这里。
&gt;&gt; Absolutely.
绝对地。
&gt;&gt; High like high signal channel high
高信号通道，高
emotionally resonant.
情感共鸣。
&gt;&gt; Absolutely.
绝对地。
&gt;&gt; But what h ends up happening is people
但最终的结果是，人们在
send loads of messages down here and
这里发送了大量信息，
then they get depressed and demotivated
然后他们感到沮丧和失去动力，
so no one's going back to me.
所以没有人再来找我了。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Like Michael Jordan used to say
。 就像迈克尔·乔丹常说的那样，
you miss every shot you don't take.
你不投篮，就不会投篮。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So basically it is I
。 是的。 是的。 所以基本上就是这样。我的
mean I think one of the things about
意思是，我认为
entrepreneurs is that you need to have
创业者需要具备的品质之一就是
resilience.
韧性。
Um like for me for me what the data I
嗯，对我来说，我
was looking for is that if I send 5,000
想要的数据是，如果我寄出 5000
letters okay which takes 25 weeks 6
封信，需要 25 周（6 个
months
月），
how many meetings does that end up in?
最终会召开多少次会议？
If that ends up with 10 meetings or 20
如果最后开了 10 次会或者 20 次会
meetings,
，那
well, now I have my number, right? And
好吧，现在我总算知道结果了，对吧？
then the second part is the meeting to
第二部分是会面成交
close ratio, right? And so to me as a
率，对吧？ 所以，作为一个
math guy, I I was just interested to
数学爱好者，我只是很想
know that it's not zero.
知道它不等于零。
&gt;&gt; Okay, I just want to make sure and I
好的，我只是想确认一下，我
could see very quickly it was not zero.
很快就发现它不是零。
Literally within first two, three months
实际上，仅仅两三个月后，
I could see it's not zero.
我就发现它不是零。
Every business needs a competitive edge.
每个企业都需要竞争优势。
And if you're great at hiring, that edge
如果你擅长招聘，那么你的优势很
should probably be your people. The A
可能就在于你的人才。
players you bring in, and I don't just
你引进的顶尖人才，我指的不仅是
mean your full-time team, but your
你的全职团队，还包括你的
freelance support, too. If you feel like
自由职业支持人员。 如果你觉得
your talent isn't quite cutting it, then
自己的才能还不够突出，那么
I want you to take another look at our
我希望你再了解一下我们的
sponsor, Fiverr Pro. Fiverr Pro is
赞助商 Fiverr Pro。  Fiverr Pro 是
Fiverr's premium offering, where every
Fiverr 的高级服务，其中每位
freelancer is handvetted, so you're
自由职业者都经过严格筛选，因此
guaranteed top quality every single
每次都能保证提供最高质量的服务
time. What's brilliant about Fiverr Pro
。  Fiverr Pro 的出色之处在于，
is that you're picking from very
您可以
experienced talent in marketing, web app
从营销、Web 应用程序
development, AI, and 750 other
开发、人工智能以及其他 750 个
categories. And these are people that
类别中经验丰富的专业人士中进行选择。 这些人
can swoop in and lead the more complex
可以挺身而出，领导
projects that your team might not be
你的团队可能
capable of handling yet. And because
暂时无法处理的更复杂的项目。 而且由于
it's a personalized service, a Fiverr
这是一项个性化服务，Fiverr
Pro hiring expert will find the help
Pro 的招聘专家会
your business needs for you. They'll
为您找到您的企业所需的帮助。 他们不仅会
hire them and manage your outsourced
负责招聘，还会全程管理您的外包
projects end to end, too. And if you're
项目。 如果您
not happy with your freelancers work,
对自由职业者的工作不满意，
then you get your money back. they are
您可以获得退款。 他们
that confident in their talent. So to
对自己才华非常有信心。 所以，不妨
give it a shot, head to fiverr.com/diary
一试，前往 fiverr.com/diary
and for 10% off your first order, use
，首次下单即可享受 10% 的折扣，使用优惠
code diary.
码 diary。
I think one of the the most formative
我认为
experiences you can give your children,
你能给孩子提供的最具塑造性的经历之一，
which I got at 16 through through 16 to
也是我在 16 岁到
19 years old, which is what I did, was
19 岁期间所经历的，就是从事
working in cold teley sales. So my job
电视推销工作。 所以我
at 16 years old, was to call people at
16岁时的工作是晚上
9:00 p.m. cold and try and get them to
9点给别人打电话。 天气寒冷，但还是想办法让他们
buy windows and doors. And it taught me
购买门窗。 它教会了我
the exact lesson you're describing,
你所描述的那种道理，
which is yes, 80% of people tell you to
那就是，没错，80% 的人会让你
off.
滚蛋。
&gt;&gt; 98% say that, but doesn't matter.
98%的人都这么说，但这无关紧要。
&gt;&gt; I always say like 80 80% told me to
我总是说，大约有 80% 的人让我
off. 15% said it in a nice way. And then
滚蛋。  15%的人用比较委婉的方式表达了他们的看法。 然后，
5% were at least receptive to what I had
至少有 5% 的人愿意接受我的
to say.
观点。
&gt;&gt; Maybe 1% close, but when you understand
或许只有 1% 的接近，但当你理解了
that, you think of life through that
这一点，你就会用这种
lens.
视角来看待生活。
&gt;&gt; And actually, Stephen, I had the almost
事实上，斯蒂芬，我的
same experience. So my father was an
经历也几乎和你一样。 我父亲是一位
entrepreneur. He was really smart at
企业家。 他非常擅长
identifying what I call offering gaps,
发现我所说的市场空白，
like things that should exist in the
比如世界上应该存在
world but didn't. And he would get these
但却不存在的东西。 他白手起家，让这些
businesses off the ground with no money.
企业步入正轨。
I saw him do it repeatedly. His downfall
我亲眼看到他多次这样做。 他的失败
was he was very aggressive in growing
在于他过于激进地发展
the businesses. And so they didn't have
业务。 所以它们没有
staying power. There was almost no
持久力。 公司几乎没有
equity, always very levered. So I he
股权，杠杆率一直很高。 所以他
went bankrupt eight or nine times,
破产了八九次，
right? Repeatedly.
对吧？ 反复。
When I was um when I was about 11 or 12
当我……嗯，大概 11 或 12
years old, my brother and I, we were
岁的时候，我和我哥哥就像
like his board of directors, okay?
他的董事会成员一样，好吗？
Because he had nobody else. The three of
因为他没有别的依靠了。
us would sit down at night to figure out
我们三个晚上会坐下来，想办法
how to make the business last for one
让生意再撑
more day. Okay? Everything's caving in,
一天。 好的？ 一切都崩溃了，
the creditors are caving in, the
债权人都崩溃了，
business is collapsing. How do we make
公司要倒闭了。 我们怎样才能让它再撑
it work for one more day? And then the
一天？ 然后
next night we'd get together and how do
第二天晚上我们又聚在一起，讨论如何才能
we make get it work for one more day
让它再维持一天
again? Right
？ 我
at 16 and I don't know why my dad did
16岁那年，我不知道我爸爸为什么
this but I'm so grateful that he did. He
这么做，但我非常感激他这么做。
was at that time he had a gold jewelry
当时他在迪拜拥有一家黄金首饰
factory in Dubai and he was going cold
工厂，他亲自挨个
calling in person to jewelry shops to
打电话给珠宝店，
buy his jewelry that he was
推销他自己
manufacturing. So he took me with him on
生产的首饰。 所以他经常带我一起去
many of these trips and I was 16 just
旅行，当时我才16岁，跟
like you, right? So we would uh take the
你一样，对吧？ 所以我们就
taxi from Dubai to Abu Dhabi and now
从迪拜打车到阿布扎比，现在那里到处
there's all these gold shops.
都是金店。
He doesn't know any of them, right? And
他一个也不认识，对吧？
he's going one after the other after the
他一个接一个地进行着
other after the other. And I would be
。 如果
fifth shop he makes a sale.
他第五家店能卖出去一笔生意，我会感到非常惊讶。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And it's a very small sale because
。 而且由于
he has no trust and all that, but he's
他缺乏信任等等原因，这笔交易金额非常小，但他还是
made the sale. Then I noticed that after
完成了交易。 然后我注意到，
3 months, we go back to that same shop.
3个月后，我们又回到了那家店。
We made the little sale to the guy
我们把那小东西卖给了
brings out tea. He there's a there's a
端茶过来的那个人。 他那里有
lot of chemistry, bigger order, and then
很多化学反应，订单量更大，然后
I saw the orders increase, right? And
我看到订单增加了，对吧？
then he's continuing to do that. And I I
然后他还在继续这样做。 我和
went with him to DohaQatar
他一起去了卡塔尔多哈，结果又发生了
uh Qatar and again the same thing. It
同样的事情。
was like, you know, I saw how those
你知道，我当时看到那些
doors opened
门打开，也
&gt;&gt; and I saw how it didn't matter to him
看到
when they closed. That was irrelevant to
门关上时他毫不在意。 对他来说，那无关紧要
him. You know,
。 你知道，这
&gt;&gt; really interesting new way to think
真是一种很有趣的新思考方式，
about it because what you're saying
因为你刚才说的
there is actually when you get that one,
其实是，当你得到那个东西的时候，
yes, it's actually a seed that's being
是的，它实际上是一颗正在
planted that can grow into something.
播下的种子，可以长成某种东西。
&gt;&gt; We just care about the ratio and the
我们只关心比例和
number. Okay. So, what effort did it
数量。 好的。 那么，这需要付出哪些努力呢
take? Like I was saying, if I send 5,000
？ 就像我刚才说的，如果我寄出 5000
letters and I get 20 meetings,
封信，能得到 20 次会面机会，
that's awesome.
那就太棒了。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; I mean, that's a fantastic ratio because
我的意思是，这个比例非常棒，因为每
one sale is going to get me about
卖出一件商品就能给我带来大约
200,000 or 300,000. It's a significant
20 万或 30 万的收入。 这笔
amount, right? I mean, so that I don't
金额相当可观，对吧？ 我的意思是，这样我就
need large numbers and
不需要很大的数字，
&gt;&gt; but the lifetime value of that,
但它的终身价值却非常
&gt;&gt; it's huge. Yeah. Yeah. I mean I mean uh
巨大。 是的。 是的。 我的意思是，我
these uh these relationships I got then
拥有的这些关系，它们现在
they're still with me,
仍然和我在一起，
&gt;&gt; you know, so it's uh it's it's like
你知道，所以就像
forever. Here's a philosophical way to
永远一样。 这里有一个适合所有人的哲学思考方式：
which is you can remember probably
你可能记得
conversations you had in your life that
生活中发生过一些
you thought were totally
你认为完全
inconsequential, but then 8 years later
无关紧要的对话，但 8 年后，
that seed became a business
这些对话的种子却发展成了商业
relationship. The example I always give
关系。 我经常举的例子
is when I was 14, I applied for the
是，我14岁的时候申请当
apprentice. They did this like junior
学徒。 他们就像BBC的初级学徒节目那样做这件事
apprentice on the BBC. And it's a long
。 这
story, 35,000 kids in London and across
说来话长，伦敦和英国各地共有 35,000 名儿童
the UK applying. I met a kid in the line
申请。 我在排队参加试镜的时候，遇到一个孩子
while I was queuing up for my audition.
。
and he said to me, "Oh, my dad runs this
他对我说：“哦，我爸爸经营着一家价值
um $500 million company." And I was
五亿美元的公司。” 我当时
like, "Yeah, whatever." Like not
就想，“是啊，随便吧。” 好像没
interested. I went through the
兴趣。 我参加了
auditions. I didn't and didn't end up
试镜。 我不知道为什么，最终没能
getting on in the show for whatever
入选那个节目
reason. But then I ended up cuz we were
。 但后来我还是去了，因为
waiting in the queue that day. I was
那天我们在排队。 我
really nice to this kid and I added him
对这个孩子很好，还在
on Facebook. 5 years later, I get a
脸书上加了他好友。 五年后，我
message on Facebook. Hey, 5 years later,
在 Facebook 上收到一条消息。 嘿，5 年过去了，
although I didn't get on the show, which
虽然我没能参加那个节目，但
investment in my company if I'd won. 5
如果我赢了，我的公司就能获得大约 25,000 美元的投资。
years later, I'm working on a startup.
五年后，我正在创办一家公司。
That kid from the line says, "Hey, um,
排队的那个孩子说：“嘿，嗯，
my dad has sold his business for a
我爸爸把他的公司卖了
billion dollars and I've been watching
十亿美元，
you on Facebook for the last five years.
过去五年我一直在Facebook上关注你。
My dad would love to meet you." It was
我爸爸很想见见你。” 这是
an Indian family, the Alawalias. They
一个印度家庭，阿拉瓦利亚家族。 他们
had sold a business called Euro Car
卖掉了一家名为 Euro Car
Parts. They took me to London when I was
Parts 的公司。 他们在我穷得叮当响的时候带我去了伦敦
literally so broke. I was like
。 我当时就像是在
shoplifting food to feed myself. And his
商店里偷东西充饥。 他
dad invested double what I would have
父亲投入到
won on the show into my business. Um and
我公司里的资金，是我在节目中赢得奖金的两倍。 嗯，
I and that always reminded me that like
我和这总是提醒我，
every conversation that I have is like
我进行的每一次谈话都像是在
planting a seed that at any point in my
播下一颗种子，在我人生的任何阶段，它都
&gt;&gt; sure
可能变成某种东西，
&gt;&gt; like you know
你知道，
&gt;&gt; I mean you know um I always bring up
我的意思是，你知道，嗯，我总是提起
Adam Grant's book uh uh givers and
亚当·格兰特的书，呃，《给予者和
takers. I don't know if you've seen that
索取者》。 我不知道你是否注意到，
all humans on the planet fall into one
地球上所有的人类都可以归为以下
of three categories. They are either a
三种类型之一。 他们要么是
giver or a taker or a matcher.
付出者，要么是索取者，要么是匹配者。
Okay, these are there are no other
好的，除此之外，没有其他
categories of humans. Just these are the
类型的人类了。 只有这
three categories. Now the matchers
三个类别。 现在匹配器相对来说
are relatively simple to understand.
比较容易理解。
Their mental framework is if Steven does
他们的想法是，如果史蒂文帮了
me a favor, I'm going to try to do
我一个忙，我也会尽力帮
something similar for him. You know, one
他做类似的事情。 你知道，
to one. They can do matching in the math
一对一。 他们可以心算匹配题
in their heads. The takers
。 那些与
who you don't have anything to ever do
你毫无瓜葛的索取者，总是
with are trying to scam and screw
想方设法欺骗和坑害
everyone and always take and never give.
所有人，他们只会索取而不会付出。
Okay? The takers basically go nowhere.
好的？ 那些索取者基本上哪儿也去不了。
Okay? And if you have any takers in your
好的？ 如果你生活中遇到任何想占你便宜的人
life, get rid of them. Okay? Now, the
，都摆脱他们。 好的？ 现在，
givers, what the givers do is the givers
捐赠者们，捐赠者们所做的，就是捐赠者们
um are not focused on what comes back to
并不关注
them.
他们能得到什么回报。
They just want to help you. They want to
他们只是想帮助你。 他们想要
help humanity.
帮助人类。
And what ends up happening is the
最终的结果是，整个
universe conspires to help them.
宇宙都在帮助他们。
&gt;&gt; So the givers
因此，乐于付出的人
become the most successful.
往往最成功。
Everyone is trying to give to them even
即使他们没有提出要求，每个人都在尽力帮助他们
though they're not asking for it. So
。 所以
basically
基本上，
when we and that's the book that Adam
当我们……而亚当·
Graham Grant wrote givers and takers is
格雷厄姆·格兰特写的《给予者与索取者》就是其中
one of the mental models. This is a
一种思维模型。
great mental model to have is to be a
乐于奉献是一种非常好的心态
giver. Don't play math games, you know,
。 不要玩弄金钱游戏，要
always try to make sure the other guy
始终确保对方在
gets the better end of the deal and just
交易中占上风，并且一直这样
keep going through your life that way
生活下去，
and that goodwill will compound and it
这种善意会不断积累，最终一切都会
will take care of itself.
迎刃而解。
&gt;&gt; And the time horizon, you don't worry
至于时间跨度，你不用担心
about the time horizon.
时间跨度。
&gt;&gt; You're not doing it for getting
你做这件事不是为了得到
something back. That's the key. You're
回报。 这是关键所在。 你
not doing any mathematics like I'm going
不会像我一样做任何数学运算
to do. You're not calculating. I'm going
。 你没有进行计算。 我这样
to do this so XYZ happens. You're just
做是为了让XYZ发生。 你只是在
doing it. End of story. I was sat with
做这件事而已。 故事到此结束。 昨晚我和
my girlfriend last night. She runs a
女朋友坐在一起。 她经营一家
breath work business. So, she's
呼吸疗法公司。 所以，她
essentially a soloreneur. Um, and she's
本质上是一位独立创业者。 嗯，她现在正处于
at that point where she's trying to
努力扩大
scale. In fact, I just meet so many I
规模的阶段。 事实上，我遇到过很多这样的企业主，我
think actually ran a survey before and
之前还做过一项调查，结果显示
the vast majority of business owners are
绝大多数企业主都
in that theme category, that small small
属于这个类别，也就是小型
sort of business category. It's the back
企业类别。 正是这些幕后推手，
startups are the backbone of our
创业公司才是我们经济的支柱
economy. But they they come to me with
。 但他们都带着
the same problem which is maybe I
同样的问题来找我，那就是也许我最初是以
started as an individual. I've got high
个人身份开始的。 我的
demand and now I'm a bottleneck and I
需求量很大，现在成了瓶颈，我
don't know how to get out of being like
不知道该如何摆脱
a freelancer. How does the freelancer
自由职业者的身份。 自由职业者如何才能
become an agency? And the thing I was
成为一家代理公司？
chatting to my girlfriend about last
昨晚我和女朋友聊天时，聊到
the steps she hasn't taken yet is to
她还没有采取的措施是
hire someone exceptional. And so many
聘请一位杰出的人才。 很多
founders come to me, these early stage
创业者，尤其是早期
founders, they're like, uh, like I I my
创业者，都会来找我，他们会说，嗯，我的
customers like me, I do it better. I
客户喜欢我，我做得更好。 我
don't trust anybody. I I wondered if you
不信任任何人。 我想知道你是否有
had like a mental model for thinking
一个思考这个问题的思维模型
about
，因为如果你看看像
people like Elon Musk and Steve Jobs,
埃隆·马斯克和史蒂夫·乔布斯这样的人，
they believe their number one job is
他们认为他们最重要的工作是
recruiting.
招聘。
The first 3,000 people who joined SpaceX
加入 SpaceX 的前 3000 名员工
all personally interviewed by Elon.
都接受了埃隆·马斯克的亲自面试。   好好
Just think about that. Those are 3,000
想想。 那可是3000个
hires. Think about the number of
新员工啊。 想想要
interviews to get the 3,000 hires. Okay?
招到 3000 名员工需要进行多少次面试。 好的？
He
他
did not believe there was any other way.
认为没有其他办法了。
And what Steve Jobs used to say is that
史蒂夫·乔布斯常说，
A players
顶尖人才
want to work with A players.
都想和顶尖人才一起工作。
The moment you start introducing B
一旦你开始引进 B 级
players,
球员，
B players will hire B and C players.
B 级球员就会雇佣 B 级和 C 级球员。
They will never hire an A player. So
他们永远不会聘用顶尖球员。 所以，当
started the moment you get a B player.
你得到一名二流球员的那一刻起，你的下坡路就已经开始了。
And so as an entrepreneur,
所以，作为一名创业者，
you know, we have a lot of demands on
你知道，我们的时间有很多要求
our time, right? But recruiting
，对吧？ 但招聘
has to be at the top and you've got to
必须放在首位，而且你必须
be willing to spend inordinate amounts
愿意
of time on recruiting. Okay? And um
在招聘上花费大量时间。 好的？ 嗯
there's, you know, there are tools that
，你知道，有一些工具
you can use. We use uh there's a company
可以使用。 我们使用一家
called Caliper. we use for
名为 Caliper 的公司。 我们将其用于入
pre-employment testing.
职前测试。
And the thing is that between the
事实是，
genetics of a human and the first 5
一个人的基因和
years of their life experience, who they
他生命最初 5 年的经历
are, their traits are hardcoded.
决定了他的性格和特征，而这些因素是无法改变的。
That is not going to change from 5 to
从5到95，这个数字不会改变。
95. Okay? So it's not like you're going
明白吗？ 所以，你不可能
to change a human. Human is the way they
改变一个人。 人就是这样
are. Okay? Now, these pre-employment
。 好的？ 现在，这些入职前
testing tests can get you data that
测试可以让你获得一些
you're not going to get in an interview.
在面试中无法获得的数据。
&gt;&gt; One of my companies I'm building at the
我目前正在创建的公司之一
moment is called cultureest.com.
叫做 cultureest.com。   正是
It's exactly this.
如此。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; Um
嗯，
I mean, you're just like preaching
我的意思是，你这就像是
preaching to the choir here.
跟信徒们说教一样。
&gt;&gt; But what I'm saying is that
但我的意思是，
&gt;&gt; it we need to get really good at
我们需要在招聘方面做得非常出色
recruiting.
。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. It's it's my absolute absolute
。 这是我的绝对
obsession. And what I found out is that
痴迷。 而我发现，
funnily enough from doing these culture
有趣的是，这正是通过这些文化
tests. So I've I've culture tested tens
测试得出的结论。 所以，我已经对
of thousands of people in the general
普通人群中的数万人进行了文化测试
population now. And the shocking part
。 而最令人震惊的部分，
was just to give you some context on
只是想给你解释一下
what it does. It benchmarks our best
它的作用。 它衡量的是我们
performing people and how they make
表现最好的员工以及他们如何做出
their decisions. The assumption here is
决策。 这里的假设是，
that culture isn't the thing you come up
文化不是你
with at the offsite. Culture is how you
在公司团建活动中想出来的东西。 文化就是你
would behave on Christmas Eve when you
在圣诞夜
get a text message from a client. Like
收到客户短信时会如何应对。
what you do there is your company
你在公司里所做的一切就是你的公司
culture. So it basically creates these
文化。 所以它基本上会提出一些
questions which simulate optimal culture
问题，模拟
in that team and it puts you in that
该团队的最佳文化，并将你置于那种
scenario and says what do you do? This
情境中，然后问你会怎么做？ 现在
is probably a good point to talk to you
或许是时候和大家谈谈
guys about culture test.com which is the
culture test.com 了，这是
website we're about to launch for anyone
我们即将推出的网站，面向所有
who has the responsibility of hiring
负责招聘的人，
someone which is probably everybody
而可能在座的各位都是招聘人员
listening. One bad hire can destroy your
。 一次糟糕的招聘就可能毁掉
entire company. So, we made
整个公司。 所以，我们创建了
cultureest.com
cultureest.com，
so that you guys at home can spot those
这样你们在家就能发现那些
red flags and avoid those hires that
危险信号，避免招到那些
might be the end of your business.
可能导致公司倒闭的员工。
Culture Test will make you your own
文化测试将为您制作
personalized culture test so that you
个性化的文化测试，以便您
can screen every single person that
可以筛选每一个
wants to be in your team and your
想要加入您团队的人、您
current team members and people that
现有的团队成员以及已经
have left to see how they align. Just go
离职的人员，看看他们是否与团队文化相符。 只需
to cultureest.com
访问 cultureest.com
and put your email address in and the
并输入您的电子邮件地址，
minute we launch, I'm going to send you
我们上线后，我会立即向您发送
an email so you can try it before
电子邮件，以便您能比
anybody else. So recruiting is really
其他人更早体验。 所以招聘真的非常
important and I think the other thing is
重要，我觉得还有一点是，
uh we're willing to hire people who may
我们愿意雇用那些可能
not do things as well as we do but
不如我们做得好的人，但
actually also what I've also found is I
实际上我也发现，我的
have so many people on my team who are
团队里有很多比
better than me.
我更优秀的人。
&gt;&gt; You know they're better at many of these
你知道他们在很多方面都比我强，
things because it's not my natural bent
因为
to do those jobs. Mhm.
做这些工作并不是我的天性。 嗯。
&gt;&gt; So that's really when you get a huge
所以，当
bang for the buck is you end up with
你最终拥有比你
team players that are way better than
优秀得多的团队成员时，你就能真正获得巨大的回报
you.
。
&gt;&gt; How do you think about firing people?
你如何看待解雇员工这件事？
Because this is the other thing I hear
因为这是我从创始人那里听到的另一种说法
from founders.
。
&gt;&gt; Hire slow, fire fast.
招聘要慢，解雇要快。
&gt;&gt; Founders really struggle with the fire
创始人往往很难做到快速放手，
&gt;&gt; and uh
但
to fire fast. I think fire fast is more
快速放手又非常重要。 我认为快速解雇
important than high or slow
比高薪或慢薪更重要，这样
and you're doing the person a a service
做对员工也有好处，
because they may be exceptional in
因为他们可能在
another role at another place. So you
其他地方的其他岗位上表现出色。 所以你既
are helping them
在帮助他们
try to find that
寻找答案，
&gt;&gt; and you're helping your other team
也在帮助你的其他团队
members.
成员。
&gt;&gt; If I was trying to work for your
如果我应聘贵
companies, what is the one
公司的工作，哪一项是绝对
non-negotiable? Like what is the trait
不能妥协的？
that I would demonstrate where you would
我到底要表现出什么特质，才会让你
immediately not even consider me?
立刻根本不考虑我？
&gt;&gt; The most important is integrity.
诚信是最重要的。
&gt;&gt; You know, I mean
你知道，我的意思是，
we we want three traits, right? We want
我们想要三个特质，对吧？ 我们需要
intelligence,
智慧、
we want integrity, and we want
正直和
willingness to work hard, right? And
勤奋的人，对吗？
none of these three are really
这三点都没有真正的
negotiable.
谈判余地。
&gt;&gt; And what does integrity mean in your
你认为诚信意味着什么
definition?
？
&gt;&gt; Well, it's absolute honesty is pretty
其实，绝对诚实很
simple. You know, it's black and white.
简单。 你知道，事情非黑即白。
and you conduct yourself with the
你的言行举止应符合
highest levels of ethical standards.
最高的道德标准。
So on all fronts when you're dealing
因此，无论是在
with a customer or internally or
与客户打交道、内部沟通还是
externally, it's the moral standards
外部交往时，道德标准都
need to be very high.
必须非常高。
&gt;&gt; When you think about your wealth, how
当你思考你的财富时，其中有
much of it has come from building
多少来自于创建
businesses versus being a great investor
企业，又有多少来自于你如何成为一名优秀的投资者，
of the capital that you manage to make
运用你
from those businesses?
从这些企业中赚取的资本？
&gt;&gt; I think currently most has come from the
我认为目前大部分增长都来自
investing side. You're very well known
投资方面。 您多年来一直是
for being a really excellent investor
一位非常优秀的投资者，这一点众所周知
over many many many many many years.
。
I'll put a graph on the screen that I
我会在屏幕上显示一张我
found which I think shows the returns of
找到的图表，我认为它显示了
your investment strategy versus the the
你的投资策略与
Dow Jones. This graph, have you seen
道琼斯指数的收益对比。 你以前见过这张图吗
that one before?
？
&gt;&gt; I haven't seen it this way, but people
我以前没见过这种情况，但人们确实会
put up all kinds of things. Yeah.
张贴各种各样的东西。 是的。
&gt;&gt; I mean, all this says is that you're
我的意思是，这一切都说明你
extremely good at investing. So, I want
非常擅长投资。 所以，我想
to know if I if I'm in starting my
知道我是否已经走上了
investing career. I'm working in a
投资生涯的起步阶段。 我
nineto-five job at the moment. I've got
目前从事朝九晚五的工作。 我
a couple of thousand dollars in my my
的银行账户里有几千美元
bank account. How should I be thinking
。 我应该如何看待
about investing? Should I be investing?
投资？ 我应该投资吗？
So,
所以，要想在
investing.
投资中获得好的结果，有三件事至关重要。
um starting capital, how much the amount
嗯，启动资金，也就是你最初投入的金额；投资
length of the runway, how long are you
期限，也就是你打算投资多久；
&gt;&gt; and the rate of return.
以及投资回报率。
Okay. So before I answer your question,
好的。 所以在我回答你的问题之前，
I want to tell you a story. So and this
我想先给你讲个故事。 这
is a true story.
是个真实的故事。
Um, in 1623
嗯，1623 年
in New York, the Native American Indians
在纽约，
in New York who owned the island of
拥有曼哈顿岛的纽约印第安人
Manhattan, the Dutch settlers wanted to
，荷兰殖民者想要
buy the island. And so they went to the
购买该岛。 于是他们去找
Indians and said, "We'd like to buy the
印第安人说：“我们想买下
island of Manhattan, great natural
曼哈顿岛，那里有绝佳的天然
harbors. It can be a great place for
港口。这对我们来说会是个好地方
us." And the Indians and the Dutch
。” 印第安人和荷兰人
reached an agreement to sell the island
达成协议，以
of Manhattan for $23.
23 美元的价格出售曼哈顿岛。
And when people hear that, they think,
人们听到这个消息，就会想：
"Oh, the Indians got taken." You know, I
“哦，印第安人被俘虏了。” 你知道吗，我觉得
don't know of Manhattan for $23 is
曼哈顿只要 23 美元简直太
ridiculous. But let's say let's say the
离谱了。 但假设
Indians had a trust officer who they
印第安人有一位信托官员，他们让他把这
said invest this $23 for the benefit of
23 美元投资于部落的利益，
the tribe and try to do a decent job.
并努力做好本职工作。
Right now there's something known as the
现在有一种叫做“
rule of 72.
72法则”的东西。72
And the rule of 72 is a is a very
法则是一条非常
important rule and I wish they would
重要的法则，我希望
teach it more in high schools and
中学和小学都能更多地教授它
elementary school. It tells us how long
。 它告诉我们
it takes money to double. And it's a
资金翻倍需要多长时间。 这是
kind of a mathematical hack. So for
一种数学上的技巧。
example,
例如，
if I'm going to get a 7% return and I do
如果我要获得 7% 的回报，我进行
72 / 7, that's approximately 10.
72 / 7 的操作，大约是 10。
And at the 7% return, it's going to take
按照 7% 的回报计算，这笔
10 years for the money to double. 7%
钱需要 10 年才能翻倍。  7%的
compounded will take 10 years. If I have
复利需要10年才能到期。 如果年
a 10% return,
回报率为10%，
it will take 7 years. 72 divided by 10
需要7年时间。  72 除以 10
is 7. If I have a 15% return, it will
等于 7。如果我获得 15% 的回报率，需要
take 5 years. 72 divided by 15 is five
5 年时间才能实现。  72 除以 15 约等于 5
approximately.
。
And if I have a 20% return, it'll take
如果收益率为 20%，则需要
three and a half years. So this rule of
三年半的时间。 所以，
72 is a nice hack. And it's very
72法则真是一个不错的技巧。
important to know how long money takes
了解资金翻倍需要多长时间非常重要，
to double because then we can start
因为这样我们就可以开始
doing a lot of math in our heads. So
在脑海中进行大量的计算了。 所以，
when we look at these Indians with the
如果我们看看这些印度人，
$23 if they were getting a 77% return
他们投入了 23 美元，如果获得 77% 的回报，
it would become $46 in 10 years and then
10 年后将变成 46 美元，
it would become $92 in 20 years and $184
20 年后将变成 92 美元，
in 30 years so on. Now if you go 100
30 年后将变成 184 美元，以此类推。 现在，如果你往前推 100
years
年，那
right it's 10 periods of 10
就是 10 个 10 的周期，10 个
and 10 periods of 10 is 2 ^ of 10
10 的周期是 2^10，2
and 2 ^ of 10 is 1,024.
^10 是 1024。
So we throw away the 24 because we don't
所以我们舍弃了 24，因为我们不想让
want to complicate the math. So at 7%
计算变得复杂。 如果年利率为 7%，持续
for a 100 years you would have a
100 年，那么我们
thousand times what we started with. And
最终得到的金额将是最初的 100 倍。
this is why because compounding becomes
这是因为复利运算会变得
nonlinear. People have a hard time
非线性。 人们很难理解它
getting their hands around it. So
。
&gt;&gt; nonlinear meaning
非线性意味着
&gt;&gt; it's not going up in a straight curve.
它不是沿直线上升的。
It's going up in a
它像
&gt;&gt; hockey stick.
曲棍球棒一样向上弹跳。
&gt;&gt; Hockey stick club. Yeah. So in 1723 the
曲棍球杆俱乐部。 是的。 所以到 1723 年，
Indians would have 23,000. It would have
印第安人将拥有 23,000 人。 它本来会
gone up a,000. And then if they continue
上涨1000美元。 如果他们继续保持
at the 7% in 1823 they would have 23
7% 的增长率，到 1823 年他们将拥有 2300
million.
万。
And in 1923 they would have 23 billion.
到 1923 年，他们将拥有 230 亿。
And in 2023 they'd have 23 trillion.
到 2023 年，他们将拥有 23 万亿美元。
&gt;&gt; Okay. Now the entire wealth of every
好的。 现在，美国所有男女老幼的财富总和为
States is 150 trillion.
150 万亿美元。
16th of that is not
其中16%并非
undeveloped land in Manhattan. So if the
曼哈顿的未开发土地。 因此，如果
Indians had invested at 7% a year for
印第安人在过去 400 年里每年都以 7% 的收益率进行投资
the last 400 years,
，
they would have more money than owning
他们现在拥有的钱将比拥有
the land.
土地还要多。
&gt;&gt; So they were not taken. They were given
所以他们没有被带走。 他们得到了
a fair deal, but they just didn't have a
公平的待遇，但他们没有遇到一位
good trust officer who could actually
能够真正帮助他们实现目标的优秀信托官员
make it happen for them. So the
。
magic of compounding is that we started
复利的魔力在于，我们最初
with $23
只有 23 美元，
and we end up with 23 trillion without
最终却拥有了 23 万亿美元，而
having a great rate of return. It's just
收益率却并不高。
an okay 7% is just okay. It's not great.
7%这个数字只能算一般。 不太好。
It's not bad, but it's okay. Now if you
不算差，但也还行。 现在，如果我们
go back a 100 years, so we started at
回到100年前，也就是
1623. Go back 100 years to 1523.
1623年，回到1523年。
We had 2,300 cents in 1623.
1623年我们有2300美分。2300
&gt;&gt; 2,300 cents.
美分。
&gt;&gt; $23 is 2,300 cents.
23美元等于2300美分。
&gt;&gt; Oh, okay. If they had got it
哦好的。 如果他们当初把价格
&gt;&gt; just converted to cents instead of
换算成美分而不是
dollars, right?
美元就好了，对吧？
&gt;&gt; Now, if you make it 1,000th of that,
现在，如果你把它缩小到原来的千分之一，这样
&gt;&gt; so just so I'm clear here. So, if you're
我就能明白了。 所以，如果你
saying if you went back a 100 years from
说，如果你回到100年前，
that point and you gave them just 23
你只给他们23
cents,
美分，
&gt;&gt; if you gave them two cents,
如果你只给他们2美分，
&gt;&gt; 2.3 cents to be exact, but if you just
确切地说是2.3美分，但如果你只
gave them two cents,
给他们2美分，是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; 100 years later that would be $20.
100年后，那将相当于20美元。
&gt;&gt; If you gave them 2.3 cents, 100 years
如果你当初给他们 2.3 美分，100 年
later, they'd be $23 and now it would be
后，他们就拥有了 23 美元，而现在，他们的财富将达到
the 23 trillion. Right? So what I'm
23 万亿美元。 正确的？ 所以我
trying to say is that
想说的是，
if the runway is long enough, the
如果跑道足够长，
starting capital doesn't matter.
启动资金多少并不重要。
Even the rate of return doesn't matter
即使回报率不高，
if the runway is long enough. Now so
只要跑道足够长，也无关紧要。 所以，
when people are thinking about
当人们考虑
investing,
投资时，
they have to keep a few things in mind.
他们必须牢记一些事情。
The first thing is spend less than you
首先，要
earn.
量入为出。
So, always try to save the first dollar
所以，要尽量把第一块钱存起来，
rather than the last dollar. So, if you
而不是最后一块钱。 所以，如果你
are making $50,000 a year, put 5,000
年收入 5 万美元，先存下 5000 美元，
into savings to start with and then do
然后再用这笔钱支付
the rest of your expenses after that.
其余的开支。
Now, it's very important when we saw
现在，正如我们
with this example, you start young.
从这个例子中看到的，这一点非常重要，那就是要从小开始。
So when people start working at 22 or 23
所以，当人们在 22 岁或 23 岁开始工作时，
whenever they start working they have to
无论何时开始工作，他们都必须开始
be saving then because that early money
储蓄，因为 22 岁时积累的早期资金
at 22 can compound for 50 years
可以复利增长 50 年，
and that's what we want. So we don't
而这正是我们所希望的。 所以我们不需要
need to do heroic things with finding
做任何惊天动地的事情去寻找
the next Nvidia or whatever else. We can
下一个英伟达或其他什么公司。 我们可以
just put it into an index. And the
把它放到索引里。
important thing is spend less than you
重要的是要
earn and keep putting that 5 7 10,000
量入为出，每年将那 5,7,10,000
every year into the savings. Don't go
存起来。 别带着
have a vacation in Hawaii with it. Let
它去夏威夷度假。 就
it keep compounding and just put it into
让它继续复利增长，然后把它纳入
a broad index and we don't really care.
一个宽泛的指数，我们并不在意。
&gt;&gt; So for someone who has never invested
所以对于从未投资过的人来说（
&gt;&gt; which would probably be the majority of
这可能占大多数
the audience, how do we simplify even
观众），我们如何才能
further in terms of just put it in an
进一步简化投资流程，直接将其投入
index? What does that mean? So
指数呢？ 这意味着什么？ 所以
basically,
基本上，
you could open an account at Fidelity or
你可以在富达、
Interactive Brokers or Robin Hood, any
盈透证券或者罗宾汉，
of these places. You could open a
这些地方都可以开户。 你可以
brokerage account for very little money.
用很少的钱开设一个证券账户。
&gt;&gt; And there's lots of them in every
每个
country.
国家都有很多这样的人。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And then you could just uh
。 然后你可以让
ask them to give to buy you the S&amp;P 500
他们帮你购买标普500
index, for example, and they will get
指数，例如，他们就会帮
you invested in that. And the S&amp;P 500 is
你进行投资。 标准普尔500指数
basically the top 500 companies.
基本上就是排名前500的公司。
&gt;&gt; It's the Yeah. the 500 dominant
是“是”。 美国500强
businesses in the US like Nvidia's in
企业，例如英伟达、
there and Microsoft and Apple and so on.
微软、苹果等等，都位列其中。
if it if the trend holds over the last
如果过去一个世纪的趋势得以延续，那么你每年就能获得 10% 的收益
century.
。
&gt;&gt; The S&amp;P has plenty of periods where it
标普500指数有很多时期都处于平稳状态
Uh it's somewhat overheated right now.
呃，现在有点过热了。
Uh but I think if you have a long enough
嗯，但我认为，如果你有足够长的
to time horizon and you're dollar cost
投资期限，并且采用美元成本
averaging in it's perfectly okay. Uh
平均法进行投资，那就完全没问题。 呃，
what you could also do as an alternative
你也可以考虑
is buy Burkshire Hathaway. So that's a
购买伯克希尔·哈撒韦公司。 所以这是一台
stock BRKB. So you could again tell
普通的BRKB。 所以你可以再次告诉
these people that just put it into
这些人，只要把钱投到
Burkshshire Hathaway. It's like an index
伯克希尔·哈撒韦公司就行了。 它就像一个索引，
and and again it's like set it and
设置好之后就
forget it. You don't need to think about
不用管了。 你不需要考虑
the investing side. You focus on yellow.
投资方面的问题。 你专注于黄色。
Okay. and uh keep putting this little
好的。 呃，把这笔
money away on the side and it's going to
小钱继续存起来，它就会
compound. And so at 18,
增值。 所以，如果你在 18 岁时
if you put away $5,000
存下 5000 美元，
and you fast forward to when you're 68,
快进到
50 years later, right now, if if you got
50 年后的 68 岁，假设
10% return on that money,
这笔钱每年获得 10% 的回报，
&gt;&gt; let's say, every seven years it would
每七年就会
double.
翻一番。
Okay. 72 / 10 is 7. 50 years is 7
好的。  72/10 等于 7。50 年是 7 个
doubles. 7 * 7 is 49.
双数。  7 乘以 7 等于 49。2 的
2 ^ of 7 is 128.
7 的平方是 128。
Okay? So, we can throw away the 28. Keep
明白了吗？ 所以，我们可以去掉28。保持
it simple.
简单。
You're going to have 100 times what you
你将拥有比最初多100倍的东西
started with. So, the 5,000 at 18 is
。 所以，18岁时的5000将
going to be 500,000.
变成500000。
Okay, at 19, if you put money away,
好吧，如果你在 19 岁的时候就开始存钱，
that's another 500,000.
那又是另外 50 万了。
20, you might have 10,000 you can put
20岁时，你可能可以投入1万美元
in. So, you can start seeing that over a
。所以，你会发现，随着
lifetime,
时间的推移，
you know, you're going to be having too
你的
much money.
钱会越来越多。
&gt;&gt; As you might have been able to tell, I'm
你可能已经看出来了，我对
behind high performing sports teams. I
高水平运动队背后的心理学非常着迷。 我
think it started with my love for Sir
想这一切都源于我
Alex Ferguson as a Manchester United
作为曼联
fan. So, when I was told about a new
球迷对弗格森爵士的喜爱。 所以，当有人告诉我 Netflix 有一部新剧
Netflix series that covers the rise of
讲述
the Dallas Cowboys, it immediately
达拉斯牛仔队的崛起时，我立刻就
piqued my interest. And this isn't
产生了兴趣。 这并非
because I'm mad about American football.
因为我讨厌美式橄榄球。
I'm not. I don't even watch it. But I do
我不是。 我根本不看。 但我确实了解
know about the Dallas Cowboys. And for a
达拉斯牛仔队。 对于
lot of Texans, they're much more than a
很多德州人来说，他们不仅仅是一支
sports team. I watched this series and
运动队。 我看了这部剧，
it is absolutely
它真是太
brilliant. It centers on Jerry Jones, an
精彩了。 故事围绕着杰里·琼斯展开，他是一位
oil businessman with no football
没有任何足球背景的石油商人，
background who bought the Cowboys in the
在 80 年代末收购了达拉斯牛仔队，
late 80s and transformed them into the
并将其打造成了
world. It's all about how one guy
世界上最有价值的体育特许经营权。 故事讲述的是一个男人
assembled a powerhouse team in the 1990s
在 20 世纪 90 年代如何组建了一支
made up of legendary players and coaches
由传奇球员和教练组成的强大队伍，
and through fearless decision-making led
并通过无畏的决策带领
his team to three Super Bowl victories.
球队赢得了三次超级碗冠军。
And I really enjoyed it and I think you
我非常喜欢它，我想你也会喜欢的
might too. Check out America's Team, The
。 快去看看《美国之队：
Gambler and His Cowboys, which is
赌徒和他的牛仔们》，这部剧
streaming right now only on Netflix, and
现在只在 Netflix 上播出，
they now sponsor this podcast. I've just
他们现在是本播客的赞助商。 我刚刚
invested millions into this and become a
向这家公司投资了数百万美元，并成为其
co-owner of the company. It's a company
共同所有人。 这是一家
called Ketone IQ. And the story is quite
名为 Ketone IQ 的公司。 这个故事很
interesting. I started talking about
有趣。 我
ketosis on this podcast and the fact
在播客里开始谈论生酮饮食，以及
that I'm very low carb, very, very low
我摄入的碳水化合物和糖分非常非常少
sugar, and my body produces ketones,
，我的身体会产生酮体，
which have made me incredibly focused,
这让我注意力非常集中，
have improved my endurance, have
提高了我的耐力，
improved my mood, and have made me more
改善了我的情绪，也让我更有
capable at doing what I do here. And
能力做好我在这里做的事情。
because I was talking about it on the
因为我在
podcast, a couple of weeks later, these
播客节目中谈到了这件事，几周后，
these little shots. And oh my god, the
这些小照片就出现在我伦敦总部的办公桌上。 天哪，
impact this had on my ability to
它对我的
articulate myself, on my focus, on my
表达能力、专注力、
workouts, on my mood, on stopping me
锻炼效果、情绪以及防止我
crashing throughout the day was so
一天中情绪崩溃的影响如此
profound that I reached out to the
深远，以至于我联系了
founders of the company and now I'm a
公司的创始人，现在我成为了
co-owner of this business. I highly,
这家公司的共同所有人。 我强烈
highly recommend you look into this. I
建议你调查一下这件事。 我
highly recommend you look at the science
强烈建议你了解一下
behind the product. If you want to try
该产品背后的科学原理。 如果您想
it for yourself, visit
亲自尝试一下，请访问
ketone.com/stephven
ketone.com/stephven，
for 30% off your subscription order. And
订阅订单可享 30% 的折扣。 而且，
you'll also get a free gift with your
您的第二批货物还会附赠一份免费礼物
second shipment. That's
。 那是
ketone.com/stephven.
ketone.com/stephven。
And I'm so honored that once again a
我非常荣幸，
company I own can sponsor my podcast.
我拥有的公司能够再次赞助我的播客节目。
You've been referred to as the the Dando
你曾被称作“丹多
Investor. And uh I've I've got a book
投资者”。 呃，我这里有一本书，是
here which you wrote called the Dando
你写的，叫做《丹多
Investor. What what what does this word
投资者》。  dando 这个词是什么
dando mean and why do they call you the
意思？为什么他们会称你为
dando investor? Dhando is actually a
dando 投资者？  Dhando 实际上是
word from Gujarat which is on the on the
古吉拉特邦的一个词，
western coast of India where Gandhi came
古吉拉特邦位于印度西海岸，是甘地的故乡
from. They are extremely astute business
。 他们是极其精明的
people and dando if you translate it
商人，dando 如果
directly in Gujarati
直接翻译成古吉拉特语，
it means business
意思是生意，
but it doesn't really mean business.
但实际上并不是生意。   这
What it means is it's a way of doing
意味着这种商业模式几乎
where the downside is non-existent.
没有任何弊端。
We already discussed how Mr. Branson
我们之前已经讨论过布兰森先生
is a dando investor. He had no downside.
是一位多么不择手段的投资者。 他没有任何缺点。
Uh Mr. Gates was a dando investor. He
呃，盖茨先生是个不折不扣的投资者。 他
had no downside. Mr. Walton was a dando
没有任何缺点。 沃尔顿先生是一位精明的
investor. They had no downside. So all
投资者。 它们没有任何缺点。 所以
of these people embarked on businesses,
这些人纷纷创业，在
without taking risk. And so the dando
不承担任何风险的情况下积累了巨额财富。 因此，《dando
investor was written from the
投资者》一书的写作出发
perspective of how can we minimize risk
点是如何
while keeping the returns intact.
在保持收益不变的情况下最大限度地降低风险。
&gt;&gt; You use this example of the Patels.
你以帕特尔家族为例。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。   那
&gt;&gt; What is what is that story?
是什么故事？
&gt;&gt; The Patels uh went to Uganda
帕特尔家族
more than 100 years ago. Maybe close to
一百多年前就去了乌干达。 大概是
130 years ago.
130年前吧。
&gt;&gt; It was a family. It's a ethnic group,
这是一个家庭。 这是一个印度民族，
okay, in India.
没错。
&gt;&gt; And so this ethnic group came to Uganda
于是，这个民族来到乌干达
to build the railroad. And
修建铁路。
but they're very savvy business people.
但他们都是非常精明的商人。   在过去
And over the course of the last 100 odd
一百
years uh when they were in Uganda
多年里，当他们在乌干达
through their dando methods of doing
通过他们的“丹多”经商方式
business they became very successful
成为非常成功的
entrepreneurs
企业家，
and they controlled large parts of the
并控制了
Ugandan economy and Idi came to power in
乌干达经济的很大一部分。伊迪
Uganda in the 1970s
在20世纪70年代在乌干达掌权，
and he said Africa is for Africans. So
他说非洲是属于非洲人的。 所以
what he did is he threw all the Patels
他把帕特尔家族的人全部赶了
out and he nationalized all their
出去，并将他们的所有
assets.
资产收归国有。
So now the Patels
所以，帕特尔人现在
were stateless.
成了无国籍人士。
The US took them in, the UK took them
美国接收了他们，英国接收了他们
in, Canada took some of them in. And
，加拿大也接收了一些人。
when they landed in the US, they
当他们抵达美国时，他们
basically really didn't have any skills
基本上没有任何技能
that would allow them to get good jobs,
可以让他们在美国找到好工作，尤其是
white collar jobs in the US. And
白领工作。
what a few of them started to do was
他们中的一些人开始
they realized
意识到，
that if they bought a motel, a small 10
如果他们买一家汽车旅馆，一家有 10
or 20 room motel,
到 20 个房间的小汽车旅馆，
uh the family could live in one or two
那么一家人就可以住在其中一两个
of the rooms and they could use the
房间里，然后他们可以用赎身所得的
money they got out and get a bank loan
钱去银行贷款，
and run the motel. Now motel are very
经营这家汽车旅馆。 如今，汽车旅馆是
labor intensive businesses. So what they
劳动密集型产业。 所以，
did is when a patel took over a motel,
当一个帕特尔家族接管一家汽车旅馆时，
they fired all the staff and the family
他们解雇了所有员工，然后家族成员
took over all the jobs, you know, the
接管了所有工作，你知道，包括
cleaning and front desk and everything
清洁、前台接待以及
else, right? And the Patels are
其他一切工作，对吧？ 帕特尔一家是
vegetarians and they are very they live
素食主义者，他们的
a very simple life. So when a Patel took
生活非常简单。 所以，当一个帕特尔家族的人
over a motel in an area, what they were
接管了某个地区的汽车旅馆时，
able to do is they were able to undercut
他们就能以低于
the prices of all the other motel in the
该地区所有其他汽车旅馆的价格出售商品，
area because they have no labor. They
因为他们没有劳动力。 他们
have no payroll. They have no workers
没有员工工资单。 他们没有工伤
comp, none of those things. And so they
赔偿，也没有其他任何福利。 所以，
were if everyone else is charging $25 a
如果其他人每晚收费 25 美元
night, they're charging, you know, 19 a
，他们就只收费 19 美元
night. So the occupancy was higher than
。 所以入住率比
everyone else. And they saved their
其他所有酒店都高。 他们把钱存了起来
money. And then what they would do is
。 然后他们会
buy the next motel, send the nephew to
买下一家汽车旅馆，派侄子去
run it, and then buy the next motel. And
经营，然后再买下一家汽车旅馆。
this started happening in the early '7s.
这种情况从 7 世纪 70 年代初就开始出现了。
And when you fast forward to today,
时至今日，
80% of all the motel in the US are in
美国 80% 的汽车旅馆都归
the Patel ownership.
Patel 家族所有。
80%. So the Patels make up.1%
80%。 所以帕特尔家族占美国人口的0.1%
[Music]
[音乐]
of the US population.
。
Indians make up about little over 1%
印度人约占1%多一点，
maybe 1.2 1.3%.
也许1.2%到1.3%。
Just onetenth of that is the Patels. And
帕特尔家族只占其中的十分之一。 而
this.1% population
这0.1%的人口却
is controlling 80% of the motel in the
控制着全国80%的汽车旅馆
country. And um
。 嗯，
it's because of the Dando way.
这都是因为丹多的方式。
&gt;&gt; So if I want to steal from the Dando
所以如果我想借鉴丹多的
way, you told me it's good to be a
方法，你告诉我做一个模仿者是件好事
copier. Um what are the principles of
。 嗯，丹多之道有哪些原则是
the Dando way that I need to be thinking
我需要思考的
about? Cuz you I think there was was
？ 因为我觉得那里面好像有
there nine? Yeah, there was nine
九个？ 是的，这本书总共有九条
principles in total in the book.
原则。
&gt;&gt; Well, the most important one is heads I
嗯，最重要的是正面我
win, tails I don't lose much.
赢，反面我输不了多少。
Everything we discuss today, Stephen, is
斯蒂芬，我们今天讨论的一切，
heads I win, tails I don't lose much.
正面我赢，反面我输不了多少。
When I started my business,
当我创业时，
when Bill Gates started, when Sam Walton
比尔·盖茨创业时，山姆·沃尔顿
started, when Richard Branson started,
创业时，理查德·布兰森创业时，都是遵循同样的
that was the formula.
模式。
If they won, they would win big. And if
如果他们赢了，他们将赢得巨大。 即使
they lost, they'd lose nothing. So
输了，他们也不会损失什么。 所以，
everything has to be in business
商业中的一切都必须
about risk reduction. Everything has to
围绕降低风险展开。 一切都得跟
be about free lunches. We love free
免费午餐有关。 我们喜欢免费
lunches. Okay. So, we always have to
午餐。 好的。 所以，我们必须始终
think about how do we get this done
思考如何在
without capital, without risk. Free
没有资金、没有风险的情况下完成这件事。 免费
lunches. Do you think there's an
午餐。 你认为
everybody's at the moment thinking about
现在每个人都在思考
AI and technology and these like really
人工智能和技术，以及这些非常
advanced um new innovations as an
先进的创新，这是否为人们创造了机会？
opportunity but does that create an
但这是否也为那些在
opportunity in the boring in the motel
汽车旅馆或自助洗衣店里无聊工作的人创造了机会
in the laundry mat?
？   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So you know the reality is so
。 所以你知道，现实情况是
business schools because there's nobody
商学院对创业学的研究并不多，因为没有人
going to give you consulting project for
会给你
studying entrepreneurs.
研究创业者的咨询项目。
If we really study startups in the US or
如果我们认真研究美国乃至全世界的创业公司
actually anywhere in the world, 99.99%
，就会发现 99.99%
of startups are non venturebacked.
的创业公司都没有获得风险投资支持。   那是
&gt;&gt; What What does that mean?
什么意思？
&gt;&gt; What I what I mean by that is those are
我的意思是，这些就像
your laundromat, your Chinese
你的洗衣店、你的中
restaurant,
餐馆、
your you know eBay seller, whatever,
你的 eBay 卖家、
Amazon seller, so on, right? The small
亚马逊卖家等等，对吧？ 小
businesses.
企业。
None of those companies were formed
这些公司都不是
because of venture capital. So the media
通过风险投资成立的。 所以媒体的
focuses on all the venture capital le
关注点都集中在所有风险投资
businesses. And so people think that oh
企业上。 所以人们会想，
if I have to do a startup I got to do
如果我一定要创业，那我必须从事
something in technology. Well that's
科技行业。 那大概只有
like onetenth of 1% or less. You can
千分之一甚至更少。 你可以
ignore it. You don't need to really
忽略它。 你其实不必为此
worry about it. Uh the important thing
担心。 重要的
is to be an observer
是要保持观察力，
and to look at uh what what uh my dad
看看我爸爸
would call offering gaps. So let me
所说的“供应缺口”。 那么，让我来
explain an offering gap, right? So let's
解释一下产品供应缺口，好吗？ 假设
there's a town, let's call it town A.
有一个城镇，我们称之为A镇。A
Town A. There's a barber shop in town A.
镇里有一家理发店。
Okay? Okay. And the barbers,
好吗？ 好的。 还有理发师，他是
one of many barbers doing well, etc.
众多生意兴隆的理发师之一等等。
There's another town about 30 mi away,
大约 30 英里外还有一个城镇，
town B, which also has barbers. They're
B 镇，那里也有理发师。 他们
also doing fine.
也一切都好。   在
middle of these two towns called Town C.
这两个城镇中间，正在兴起一个新的城镇，名为 C 镇。C
Town C doesn't have much of a
镇
population, but it's growing fast.
人口不多，但发展迅速。
So, the barber in town A goes to see
所以，A镇的理发师去
what the all the hoopla or town C is all
C镇看看究竟发生了什么事
about. So he makes a takes a trip there,
。 于是他去了那里，
sees that there's some increase in
发现那里的人口有所增加
population. People are moving in and he
。 人们搬进来后，他
notices there's no barber shops. Why
注意到这里没有理发店。 为什么会有
would there be any barber shops? Because
理发店呢？ 因为
it's brand new, right? So he's thinking,
它全新，对吧？ 所以他在想，
how do I do this without taking risk?
怎样才能在不承担风险的情况下做到这一点呢？
And what he does is he rents a subleas
他租了一间
leases a small storefront,
小店面，
buys some used barber equipment, and
买了一些二手理发设备，然后
then decides that one day a week he's
决定每周三
going to go into that town and cut hair
去镇上剪头发，并在店面贴了
every Wednesday and puts up a note board
一张告示牌，上面写着：“
saying, "I'm available Wednesdays."
我周三有空”。
And what happens is people start coming
于是，人们开始
in.
涌入。
They come in because they have no
他们涌入是因为他们别无选择
choice. if you don't go to this barber,
。 如果你不去这家理发店，
you got to spend half an hour driving to
你就得花半个小时开车去
one of those two towns. Now, he normally
那两个镇子中的一个。 现在，他理发通常
charges 30 bucks for a haircut.
收费30美元。
But here, he doesn't need to charge 30
但在这里，他不需要收取 30 元，
because there's an opportunity cost of
因为
the time you're saving. So, he can
你节省的时间是有机会成本的。 所以，他可以
charge 45.
收 45 美元。
So, he's charging 45 over here and then
他在这里收 45 美元，然后在
when he's in his own town, he's charging
他自己的城市里，他收
30. Now, what he what he notices is
30 美元。现在，他注意到
Wednesdays are filled up. So, he says
星期三的预约都满了。 所以，他说
Tuesday and Wednesday. Okay? And
周二和周三。 好的？
gradually what ends up happening is that
渐渐地，结果就是
and he's making 45 bucks an hour per
他把理发当成了全职工作，每次理发每小时能赚 45 美元
haircut.
。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; But the nature of capitalism is more
但资本主义的本质决定了
barbers are going to show up. So the
会有更多理发师出现。 所以
second barber comes in, the third barber
第二个理发师进来了，第三个理发师
comes in, eventually the haircut there
进来了，最后在那里理发要花
is going to be 30 bucks. It's going to
30 美元。 它会起到
neutralize. But in the meanwhile, he's
中和作用。 但与此同时，他的
doubled his business.
生意却翻了一番。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Right.
正确的。
What risk did he take? So going into
他冒了多大的风险？ 所以进军
Town C was addressing an opportunity
C 镇​​是为了弥补机会
gap. When Howard Schulz started
缺口。 霍华德·舒尔茨创办
Starbucks,
星巴克时，
he saw an offering gap. He thought that
他看到了市场空白。 他认为
what Italians love about cafes
意大利人喜欢咖啡馆的原因，
might be what Americans love too.
可能也是美国人喜欢咖啡馆的原因。
It didn't exist, right? And he went and
它并不存在，对吧？ 他真的去做了
did it. you know that barber that moves
。 你知道，第一个搬到 C 镇的那家理发店生意特别
having a great time because there's no
好，因为没有
competition. One of your points when
竞争。
you're talking about the Dando method is
你在谈到丹多方法时提到的一点是，要
this idea of creating a durable moat.
创造一个持久的护城河。
It's point four of the nine.
这是九分之四。
&gt;&gt; So, so sometimes what happens is that
所以，有时候会发生这样的情况：
you start a business every business
你创办一家企业，而所有企业在创业之初都
starts off without a moat.
没有护城河。
&gt;&gt; What is a moat?
什么是护城河？
&gt;&gt; We have a castle.
我们有一座城堡。
a knight in charge of the castle to keep
一名骑士负责守卫城堡，抵御
the invaders away. And one of the ways
入侵者。
to keep the invaders away is you put a
抵御入侵者的方法之一就是在
motor water around the castle. So when
城堡周围设置自动喷水装置。 所以，当
you put a motor water around the castle,
你在城堡周围设置水坝时，就
it makes it harder for anyone to take
使得任何人更难攻占
the castle.
城堡。   拥有
&gt;&gt; And a business with a moat around it is
护城河的企业，
a business that competitors
竞争对手
will have a difficult time take business
很难从中抢走生意
away from. So what can happen with our
。 那么，我们
barber in town C? Humans are creatures
C镇的理发师会发生什么事呢？ 人类是
of habits. We don't like to change our
习惯的动物。 我们不喜欢
barber every month. We like the same
每个月都换理发师。 我们喜欢同一个
barber. So if he's competent and good,
理发师。 所以，如果他能力强、素质高，
what's going to end up happening is that
最终的结果就是
his client base will stay with him. What
他的客户群会一直跟着他。
about loyalty points? I was just struck
会员积分呢？
the other day when I was shopping in LA
前几天我在洛杉矶的
at Airwan, which is a supermarket here
Airwan超市购物时，突然想到了一件事。Airwan是洛杉矶的一家超市，
in LA, and I someone had recommended to
我
me on the plane, which actually goes to
在飞机上的时候有人向我推荐过。这其实也印证了
your point about actually give a great
你说的要提供优质产品的观点，
product because an airline hostess on my
因为我
flight over here went, "Oh, you're um
飞来的时候，一位空姐说：“哦，你……
you're on keto diet. You need to go
你在进行生酮饮食。你应该去
check out Air1." I got to So, that's the
看看Air1。” 所以，这条
recommendation
建议
&gt;&gt; that's 10x more powerful than any ad or
比任何广告或其他推广方式都有效 10 倍
anything else they could drive.
。
&gt;&gt; And I went there.
我去了那里。   是的
&gt;&gt; When I landed cuz I needed a supermarket
我下飞机是因为我需要去超市，
and didn't know the place. But then
但我不知道超市在哪里。 但
interestingly, when I was at the
有趣的是，
checkout yesterday after my second
昨天我第二次光顾后结账时
visit, the lady at the checkout goes,
，收银员问道：
"Hey, are you are you an Air1 member?"
“嘿，请问您是 Air1 会员吗？”
And I was like, "Air1 member?" And she
我当时就想：“Air1成员？” 她
was, "It does cost." She went, she was
说道：“这确实要花钱。” 她去了，她很
honest. She went, "It costs money, but
诚实。 她接着说：“这需要花钱，但
here's what you get." She goes, "On this
你能得到这样的结果。” 她接着说：“
order today, you would have got 10% off
今天这单订单，您可以享受
this entire order. It's expensive one."
全单九折优惠。这单东西很贵。”
And she goes, "And we give you a drink
她接着说：“我们每个月都给你一杯饮料
every month." She listed all the things
。” 她把所有东西都列举了一遍
off.
。
&gt;&gt; I signed up and bought the membership
我注册并购买了会员
tow. I tell you now,
拖车服务。 我现在就告诉你，
&gt;&gt; I'm not going anywhere else.
我哪儿也不去。
I don't know what it is, but now that
我不知道这是为什么，但既然
I'm a member and I have the app, I'm not
我已经是会员并且有了这款应用，我就不会
going anywhere else.
去别的地方了。
&gt;&gt; Well, that's now that's the hack that
这就是亚马逊这次的黑客攻击
Amazon did, right? With Prime and um
，对吧？ 大约
two or three years ago, I was uh I was
两三年前，我和 Prime 一起
seated at dinner next to Bill Gates. You
吃饭时，我坐在比尔·盖茨旁边。 你
know, my middle name is Forest Gump.
知道吗，我的中间名是阿甘正传。
These things happen once in a while. And
这种事偶尔会发生。
Bill is Bill is describing to me how the
比尔正在向我解释
business model of Costco and the
Costco 和
business model of Amazon is illegal.
亚马逊的商业模式是如何违法的。
Okay. So I said, "Why is it illegal?" He
好的。 于是我问：“为什么这是违法的？” 他
said, "When you when you put a
说：“当你收取
membership fee,
会员费时，
is you're locking them in." Mhm.
你实际上是在把消费者锁定在会员制度里。” 嗯。
&gt;&gt; Which means the consumer is no longer
这意味着消费者不再
going after the lowest price because
追求最低价格，因为他们的
they the distortion in their behavior.
行为发生了扭曲。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So now the FTC doesn't believe
好的。 所以现在联邦贸易委员会认为
it's illegal, but Bill Gates does. And I
这并不违法，但比尔·盖茨却认为违法。 我当时就在
was just thinking, well, that's because
想，那是因为
you're competitive with Amazon,
你和亚马逊是竞争对手
&gt;&gt; you know.
。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah.
。 是的。
&gt;&gt; That Prime thing with Amazon is super
亚马逊的Prime会员服务真是太
smart.
聪明了。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And and that was taken from
。 而且，那东西是从
Costco.
Costco 拿来的。
&gt;&gt; Oh, okay. you know, but basically, yeah,
哦好的。 你知道，但基本上来说，是的，锁定锁定
the lock in lock in is very powerful.
非常强大。
&gt;&gt; One company I wanted to talk to you
我想和你谈谈
about was Apple because Apple, I find,
苹果公司，因为我觉得苹果
is a really interesting company. You
是一家非常有趣的公司。 你曾
talked about being a copycat, kind of
说过自己像个模仿者，有点像姗姗来迟，
arriving later to the party with new
带着新
things.
东西加入进来。
They've kind of been a story of both
他们的故事某种程度上反映了
sides of the equation. They've been
问题的正反两面。 他们似乎一直都很有
innovative, it seems, especially under
创新精神，尤其是在
Steve Jobs. And more recently,
史蒂夫·乔布斯的领导下。 而最近，
&gt;&gt; I mean, they were like copying other
我的意思是，他们就像是在模仿其他
people, but now I'm not even sure what
人，但现在我甚至不确定
they are. Well, so Apple is a very
他们到底在做什么。 苹果公司是一家非常
unusual company in that everything
不寻常的公司，因为它的一切都
emanated from one guy.
源于一个人。
&gt;&gt; Okay? And that one guy has been gone for
好的？ 那个人已经离开
a long time. And if you look at Apple,
很久了。 而如果你看看苹果公司，
basically nothing new has come out since
自从他离开后，基本上就没有什么新产品推出了
he left.
。
We don't have a Steve Jobs at Apple. We
苹果公司没有史蒂夫·乔布斯。 我们和
Disney. you know, they had to buy Pixar
迪士尼也发生了同样的事情。 你知道，他们不得不收购皮克斯，
because there was no Disney anymore. Mr.
因为迪士尼已经不复存在了。
Disney was gone. And so Apple actually I
迪士尼先生去世了。 因此，我认为投资苹果公司实际上存在
somewhat risky
一定的风险
&gt;&gt; as an investment.
。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes. Because if the form factor So
。 因为如果外形尺寸……
currently humans walk around with a
目前人类
brick in their pockets or in their
口袋里或手里拿着一块砖头
hands,
，那么
at some point that form factor is going
在某个时候，这种外形尺寸将会
to change. It may be integrated into
改变。 它可能会被集成到
something we wear or some other more
我们穿戴的物品或其他更符合人体
ergonomic situation
工程学的环境中，而这个环境
that may or may not be Apple. And in
可能与苹果公司有关，也可能无关。
fact, more likely not to be Apple. It's
事实上，更有可能不是苹果公司。
probably some guy in a garage somewhere.
可能是某个家伙在某个车库里干的。
And so if they are smart enough to find
所以，如果他们足够聪明，能
the guy in the garage early enough and
及早找到车库里的那个人并
buy them, they're okay. And bring them
买下他们，那就没问题了。 把他们招
in as the next street jobs, that's okay.
进来做下一批街头工作，这没问题。
But even there the odds are low.
但即便如此，可能性也很低。
&gt;&gt; What does this say to you about
这让你对创始人有什么看法
founders?
？
The specialness of founders. Are they a
创始人的特殊性。 它们是
unique animal or can you swap them out
独一无二的动物吗？还是可以用其他动物代替，
and still be tremendously successful?
仍然能取得巨大的成功？
&gt;&gt; Well, I would I would say that
嗯，我觉得这里面有
there are a lot of elements of luck. So,
很多运气的因素。
first of all, founders are all great at
首先，创始人都很擅长
what I call offering gaps, right? They
我所说的“产品/服务缺口”，对吧？ 他们
find something that the world doesn't
发现世界上缺少某种东西，而这种东西又是他们
have that needs etc and they go after
需要的，然后他们就去追求
it.
它。
Sometimes what happens with the offering
有时候，产品/服务
gaps is a moat gets built right someone
差距会形成护城河，比如有人
starts Visa it becomes a multi company
创办了Visa，它发展成为一家多家公司，
or American Express and so on and it
或者像美国运通等等，它会
&gt;&gt; like Apple with their ecosystem their
像苹果公司凭借其
closed ecosystem
封闭的生态系统一样持续发展壮大。
&gt;&gt; but
但
eventually will go to zero
最终，所有企业都会走向衰落，
and so it very well could be that a
所以一个
business could last for 50, 100, 200
企业完全有可能持续50年、100年、200
years, 150 years
年、150年，甚至远远
uh could last well past the founders's
超过创始人的
lifetime.
寿命。
Those are businesses which were built
这些企业都是秉持着
with a lot of principles and a lot of
许多原则和
great core values. You know the founder
优秀的价值观而建立的。 你知道
of IKEA,
宜家的创始人吗？
every decision he took was with a 500y
他做的每一个决定都是着眼于未来500
year view.
年的发展。
How many businesses think with a 500y
有多少企业会以500
year view?
年为单位进行思考？
and
还有
IKEA, you know, I was I was uh studying
宜家，你知道，我当时在研究
IKEA. Some very remarkable things about
宜家。 它有一些非常特别之处
it. First of all, he never ever took
。 首先，他从来没有
debt. Every single store they built,
负债。 他们建造的每一家门店，
they built out of retained earnings and
都是用留存收益和
cash. He never took debt. And I've
现金建造的。 他从不负债。 我对
studied business failure quite a bit.
企业失败进行了相当深入的研究。
The single biggest reason why businesses
企业失败的最大单一原因
fail is leverage. They owe people money
就是杠杆过高。 他们欠别人钱，
and they can't pay it back and that
还不起，然后就
they're gone. So IKEA has never taken
消失了。 所以宜家从未
debt. If you never take debt as a
负债。 如果零售商从不负债
retailer, you're going to grow slower,
，发展速度就会比较慢，
right? You got to keep uh kind of
对吧？ 你必须不断地
bringing in the cash, but it's a very
赚回现金，但它的
solid foundation
基础非常稳固，
because
因为
it's it's on a rock solid balance sheet.
它的资产负债表非常稳健。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; And and such. And um his second
诸如此类。 他的第二个
principle was
原则是，
no two IKEA stores can be the same. So
没有两家宜家商店可以完全相同。 所以
what he said is that whenever we opening
他的意思是，每当我们开设
a new IKEA store, there has to be some
一家新的宜家门店时，都必须在
that is going into that store that does
这家门店中加入一些
not exist in our previous stores because
我们以前的门店所没有的创新，因为
he says that if I don't keep innovating,
他说如果我不不断创新，
I'm done. And so if we don't notice it
我就完了。 所以，如果我们
because we think all the IKEAs are the
因为认为所有的宜家都
same, but actually if you study them and
一样而没有注意到这一点，但实际上，如果你研究它们，
look at when they were when they were
看看它们是什么时候
built, etc., you start seeing these
建造的等等，你就会开始看到它们
making.
正在进行的这些渐进式变化。
&gt;&gt; That's a really interesting idea that I
这是一个非常有趣的想法，我
could implement into everything that I
可以将其应用到我
do, which is just making sure that every
所做的每一件事中，那就是确保
podcast I do,
我做的每个播客
&gt;&gt; there's one new experiment or innovation
都有一个新的实验或创新，
or every piece of work you do, whatever
或者你做的每一项工作，无论
team you're in is just to run out one
你身处哪个团队，都要进行一次
experiment in every Absolutely. But you
实验。绝对如此。 但你
have to make it measurable, right? or
必须让它可衡量，对吧？
else it's not a
否则就不是
&gt;&gt; experiment. So, um you also talk about
实验了。 所以，嗯，你也提到要
making fewer big infrequent bets.
减少大额不频繁的投注。
&gt;&gt; Who who's that relevant for and in what
这与谁相关？在什么
context?
情况下相关？
one of the things that Warren Buffett
沃伦·巴菲特
says, he says that you get a punch card
说过，你可以拿到一张打孔卡，
lifetime and each time you buy a stock,
一生可以打 20 次孔，每次购买股票，就会
it's one punch that's gone. So what what
消耗一次打孔机会。 所以
Warren is saying is
沃伦的意思是，
if there was a rule which said that you
如果有一条规定说你
whole life,
一生中不能购买超过 20 只股票，那么
what would happen is you would be very
你就会非常
thoughtful
谨慎地选择
about what you bought. Okay? And chances
购买的股票。 好的？ 而且
are those decisions might be good
这些决定很可能是明智的
decisions because uh you only have 19
决定，因为，呃，你只剩
left and then you only have 18 left etc.
下 19 个了，然后只剩下 18 个了，以此类推。
So
所以
in in venture investing,
在风险投资中，
a very small sliver of companies that
只有极少数
venture capitalists invests in do well,
风险投资家投资的公司能够成功，
right? There's a high high burnout rate.
对吧？ 员工倦怠率非常高。
And if you look at the stock market,
如果你观察一下股市，就会发现只有
4% of listed companies
4% 的上市公司
generate 90% of the return.
创造了 90% 的回报。
So most companies that we may think
因此，我们考虑投资的大多数公司
about investing in are likely not to do
可能都不会给
&gt;&gt; for us. It's a 96% odds
我们带来好结果。 有 96% 的概率，这
that that's why the index is so
就是指数如此
important is when you buy the index
重要的原因：当你购买指数时，
you bought that 4%.
你就购买了那 4%。
And if you go pick stocks
如果你去选股，
you have one in 25 chance of getting one
你有 1/25 的机会选到那
of those 4% there. You said earlier the
4% 的优质股票之一。 你之前提到过
punch card analogy of 20 things in the
打孔卡的比喻，一张打孔卡上有 20 样东西
punch card. You got to pick 20 in your
。 你一生中要选择20个
life. If you only had three or three to
。 如果现在你只能选择三到
five things that you you would bet or
五件事进行投注或
back now,
支持（
&gt;&gt; which I think is actually kind of what
我认为这实际上就是
you do, what would those things be?
你所做的），你会选择哪三件事？
&gt;&gt; Well, I mean, uh, so I'm trying to
嗯，我的意思是，呃，所以我尽量
resist going to specific names.
避免提及具体的名字。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
。
&gt;&gt; Because I think that would hurt people
因为我觉得那样做
more than help people.
弊大于利。
&gt;&gt; Okay, that's fair. What I would prefer
好吧，这很合理。 我更希望
that people do is focus on the other two
大家关注另外两个
variables, which is the amount you're
变量，即你的
saving and the length of the runway and
储蓄金额和资金周转时间，并
focus on the index.
关注指数。
So I I I think that it's it's kind of
所以我觉得这有点像是在
like saying I want to be a great AI
说，我想成为一名优秀的AI
developer because it's the way it be.
开发者，因为这就是现状。
Well, to be a great AI developer is
成为一名优秀的AI开发者
going to take time. It's just the nature
需要时间。 这就是现状
of the situation. What do you think
。 你
about these people that day trade?
对这些从事日内交易的人有什么看法？
Because so many young people,
因为很多年轻人，
specifically men, are being sucked in by
特别是男性，都被
these adverts that you can day trade
这些广告所吸引，以为可以通过日内交易
your way to wealth.
致富。
&gt;&gt; It's not good. I think I think it's um
这不太好。 我觉得，我觉得，嗯，
the broker is going to make all the
经纪人会赚到所有的
money. Robin Hood will do well,
钱。 罗宾汉会混得好，
not you.
你不会。
&gt;&gt; Do you think anyone can make loads of
你认为有人能通过
money as a long-term day trader?
长期日内交易赚很多钱吗？
&gt;&gt; I look at it this way. If you study the
我是这么看的。 如果你研究一下
Forbes 400, the 400 richest people in
福布斯400富豪榜，也就是美国、全世界最富有的400人，
I don't see any day traders in there.
你会发现里面没有一个是日内交易员。
&gt;&gt; One of the last things I want to speak
最后我想
to you about is this idea of um circling
和你们谈谈的一件事就是“抱团取暖”这个想法
the wagons.
。   是的
&gt;&gt; Yes.
。   “
&gt;&gt; What does circling the wagons mean?
抱团取暖”是什么意思？
Warren Buffett
沃伦·巴菲特
um said that over a
曾表示，在他
50-year period of running Burkshshire
执掌伯克希尔·哈撒韦公司的50年间
Hathaway,
，
he's made hundreds of investments
他进行了数百项投资，
and only 12
但只有12项投资真正
have move the needle for Burkshire
为伯克希尔·
Hathaway. So it's the same 3 or 4% rule
哈撒韦公司带来了显著的收益。 所以，这和 3% 或 4% 的规则一样，
where if we say that Warren made
如果我们说沃伦做了
300 investments, he probably made more
300 项投资，他可能做的投资远
than 300 but let's say he made 300
不止 300 项，但假设他做了 300 个
decisions
决定，
only 12 have resulted in what we see as
只有 12 个决定最终成就了我们
Burkshshire Hathway today. And the
今天看到的伯克希尔·哈撒韦公司。 而最
important thing was not
重要的不是
the buy decision on those 12.
买入那12只股票的决定，而是永远
The important thing was never selling
不要卖掉
them.
它们。
So,
所以，“
circle the wagons is a term that comes
围成一圈”这个词源于
the 19th century when these pioneers
19 世纪，当时这些先驱者
were moving west, the wagon trails
向西迁徙，篷车小道
moving west and the native Indians would
向西延伸，而当地的印第安人
attack or bandits would attack these
或强盗会袭击这些
wagon trails. So, what they would do is
篷车小道。 所以，他们会把
they would put themselves in a circle.
自己围成一个圆圈。
Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; They would circle the wagons, then
他们会把马车围起来，然后
with their guns and so on, but the
用枪炮等武器尽力守住这个圈，但把
wagons being circled was the best
马车围起来是
off that attack.
抵御这种攻击的最佳方式。
&gt;&gt; So in effect, they circle the wagons
所以实际上，他们是在保护
around the crown jewel. So when I'm
皇冠上的明珠。 所以，当我
talking about circular wagons, what I'm
谈到循环投资时，我的
saying is that in a lifetime of
意思是，在一生的
investing, there are very few times when
投资生涯中，
you're going to actually have a huge
你真正获得巨额
multibagger.
回报的机会非常少。   那
&gt;&gt; What's that?
是什么？
&gt;&gt; A big big winner. You know, something
大赢家。 你知道，就是那种
that goes up 10x, 50x, 100x.
上涨 10 倍、50 倍、100 倍的东西。
And what you want to do is you want to
而你真正想做的，就是
effectively circle the wagons around
有效地阻止
that idea so it doesn't get sold.
这个想法被出售。
So
所以，在
invest
投资之前，我们无法知道
whether something is going to be a
某项投资是否会成为
multibagger or not. But we may figure it
高回报的投资。 但我们或许在
out after we own it.
拥有它之后就能弄明白了。
&gt;&gt; So after we we only going to know a
所以，我们只有在
business after we own it. We're not
拥有它之后才会真正了解它。 我们只有
going to know it before we own it. After
拥有它之后才会知道。
we own it, we may understand the
拥有它之后，我们或许会对这个
business well enough to know that this
行业有足够的了解，从而意识到这
is a great business. And when we figure
是一个很棒的行业。 当我们
out it's a great business,
发现这是一项很棒的生意时，
you don't want to sell that.
你肯定不想把它卖掉。
&gt;&gt; When I meet people like you, I I'm
每当我遇到像你这样的人，我
always so inspired because we spend a
总是深受鼓舞，因为我们花了
lot of time thinking about the wins, the
很多时间思考胜利和
great decisions. We've talked about
伟大的决定。 我们已经讨论过这个问题了
that. I've shown you the graph of your
。 我已经向你展示了你做出的
great decisions. What is the worst ever
伟大决定的图表。 就
decision you made in terms of financial
财务业绩而言，你做过的最糟糕的决定是什么
performance?
？
&gt;&gt; Well, I've had so many zeros.
唉，我见过太多零了。
So, I mean, uh
所以，我的意思是，呃，
&gt;&gt; or the one that got away.
或者说，那个溜走的人。
&gt;&gt; I mean, yeah. I mean so the there's
我的意思是，是的。 我的意思是，有
mistakes of commission which is uh
执行错误（也就是
things going to zero and there's
事情归零），也有
mistakes of omission. The mistakes of
遗漏错误。 疏忽造成的错误要
um far worse. Okay. So the biggest
严重得多。 好的。 所以
mistakes I have made aren't the ones
我犯过的最大错误并不是那些
that have gone to zero. The biggest
已经归零的错误。
mistakes I've made are the ones that I
我犯过的最大错误就是
sold and I shouldn't have. Where I
卖掉了那些我不应该卖的东西。 我本
should have circled the wagons and I
应该采取防御措施，但我
didn't.
没有。
and those have been very costly.
而且这些花费非常高昂。
&gt;&gt; Give me one example.
请举一个例子。
&gt;&gt; Well, so I think this was in about 13
嗯，我想这大概是13
years back 2012. I invested in uh
年前的2012年。我投资了一家
company called Fear Chrysler
名为Fear Chrysler
Automobiles. Um basically it was uh
Automobiles的公司。 嗯，基本上就是
coming out of bankruptcy after the
从金融危机后的破产中走出来
financial crisis. They had gotten rid of
。 他们已经还清了
all that debt and everything and the
所有债务，
stock was very cheap. It was about5 or 6
股票价格非常便宜。 当时大概需要50亿到60
billion uh that you could buy the whole
亿美元才能买下整个
business. One of the things I didn't pay
公司。 当时我没有
too much attention to at the time was
太注意的一件事是，
that 80% of Ferrari was inside Fiat
法拉利 80% 的股份都在菲亚特
Chrysler and they owned Ferrari 80% of
克莱斯勒旗下，他们拥有法拉利 80% 的
it and um but they had many other assets
股份，而且他们还有很多其他资产，
which I like. They had the Ram trucks
我很看好这些资产。 他们有Ram皮卡、
and Jeep and Maserati and so on. And
吉普车、玛莎拉蒂等等。
when I looked at the business, I thought
当我审视这家公司时，我认为即使
five or six billion even ignoring
不考虑法拉利，它的价值也至少是五六十亿美元
Ferrari. And I was right. So in the end,
。 我猜对了。 所以最终，
I made several times my money.
我赚的钱是投入的几倍。
And in 2017 or 2018, they took Ferrari
2017年或2018年，他们将法拉利
public. So they actually then listed the
上市。 所以他们最终还是把
company. And um it looked like that they
公司上市了。 看起来他们
had captured all the value and so I sold
已经攫取了所有价值，所以我卖掉了
I used to own approximately
我曾经拥有的大约
1% of Ferrari as part of that purchase
1% 的法拉利股份，那是我之前收购的一部分
that I had made.
。
So 80% of Ferrari was in this $5 billion
所以，法拉利80%的股份都属于这家市值50亿美元的
company. Ferrari now has a market cap of
公司。 法拉利目前的市值
almost a hundred billion.
接近一千亿美元。
if I had not done that stupid thing. So
如果我没做那件蠢事，我本可以多拥有大约十亿。 所以，
I I made a couple of hundred million on
我靠
this whole thing, but it would have been
这件事赚了几亿美元，但本来会赚得
a lot more. And all I needed to do was
更多。 我只需
just not sell it.
要不卖掉它就行了。
&gt;&gt; Do you deal in crypto at all? Do you
你从事加密货币交易吗？ 你
invest?
投资吗？
&gt;&gt; No, it's outside my competence. I don't
不，这超出了我的能力范围。 我不
understand it. I was going to say one of
明白。 我本来想说，
the things I notic about you that's
我注意到你身上有一点
quite rare for someone that deals in
非常难得，对于一个从事养蜂业（而且是数
bees, billions, is you have a smile on
十亿只蜜蜂的生意）的人来说，那就是你脸上总是带着笑容
your face. You seem like a really
。 你看起来真的是个很
genuinely happy person.
快乐的人。   如果
bees without being happy?
蜜蜂不快乐，那它们存在的意义又是什么呢？
&gt;&gt; Well, a lot of people aren't as as you
其实，很多人都不像你
know.
想象的那样。
&gt;&gt; Well, then they've lost their way
那他们肯定是在某个地方迷路了
somewhere.
。
I mean, on a daily basis, I specifically
我的意思是，我每天都会特意
ask myself, how do I want to spend
问自己，我今天想怎么度过
today? And I focus on spending it not
？ 我注重的是如何花钱，而不是如何
with the focus on maximizing money. I
最大化地赚钱。 我
focus it with maximizing what Monish
专注于最大限度地发挥莫尼什的
loves.
喜好。
And that changes all the time. But
而且这种情况一直在变化。 但事实就是如此
that's the way it is. You know
。 你知道那
&gt;&gt; what is that?
是什么吗？
&gt;&gt; Well, currently it's golf.
嗯，目前是高尔夫。
struggled with today was there wasn't
今天让我感到非常沮丧的事情之一就是没法打
going to be any golf. So I said it's
高尔夫了。 所以我说，
either Steven or golf. Should I go to
要么选史蒂文，要么选高尔夫。 我应该去找
Steven or should I go for golf? I said,
史蒂文还是去打高尔夫？ 我说，
you know what? Give the arms a rest.
你知道吗？ 让手臂休息一下。
&gt;&gt; Let's go meet Stephen.
我们去见斯蒂芬吧。
&gt;&gt; I'm glad you did. We have a You probably
我很高兴你这么做了。 我们有一个你可能
just answer this question. We have a
只需要回答这个问题的问题。 我们有个
tradition where the last guest leaves a
传统，最后一位客人会给下一位客人留下一个
question for the next not knowing who
问题，但他并不知道这个问题是留给谁的
they're leaving it for. And the question
。
left for you is if you could go anywhere
留给你的问题是，如果你现在可以立刻去任何地方
right now instantly, where would you go?
，你会去哪里？
&gt;&gt; I'd go to the golf course.
我会去高尔夫球场。
&gt;&gt; Thank you so much for everything that
非常感谢您
you do. so incredibly important and I
所做的一切。 这太重要了，我
now know why you're why people love
现在明白为什么人们喜欢
listening to you and learning from you
听你讲话、向你学习了，那
and it's because you have this most
是因为你拥有讲述
engaging stories. Thank you so much.
引人入胜的故事的非凡能力。 太感谢了。
This has always blown my mind a little
这件事一直让我有点难以置信
bit. 53% of you that listen to the show
。 经常收听该节目的听众中，有 53% 的人
regularly haven't yet subscribed to the
尚未订阅该
show. So, could I ask you for a favor?
节目。 那么，我能请你帮个忙吗？
If you like the show and you like what
如果你喜欢我们的节目，喜欢
we do here and you want to support us,
我们在这里所做的一切，并且想要支持我们，最简单的
the free simple way that you can do just
免费方法
that is by hitting the subscribe button.
就是点击订阅按钮。
And my commitment to you is if you do
我向你承诺，如果你能做到
that, then I'll do everything in my
这一点，我也会竭尽全力
power. me and my team to make sure that
。 我和我的团队会确保
this show is better for you every single
这档节目每周都能为您带来更好的体验
week. We'll listen to your feedback.
。 我们会认真听取您的反馈意见。
We'll find the guests that you want me
我们会找到您希望我
to speak to and we'll continue to do
采访的嘉宾，并继续做好我们一直在做的事情
what we do. Thank you so much.
。 太感谢了。
[Music]
[音乐]